<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Court &amp; kitchin of Elizabeth, commonly called Joan Cromwel the wife of the late usurper, truly described and represented, and now made publick for general satisfaction.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 142 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 83 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35073</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12233260</idno>
  <idno type="VID">56650</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240956369</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing C7036</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22455</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12233260</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35073)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56650)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 137:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Court &amp; kitchin of Elizabeth, commonly called Joan Cromwel the wife of the late usurper, truly described and represented, and now made publick for general satisfaction.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20], 133 [i.e. 145] p. : port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho. Milbourn for Randal Taylor ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Satire on the Protector's wife, notably on her alleged parsimony in household mangement; includes family anecdotes and a collection of recipes purporting to be those used by her.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: portrait lacking.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Cromwell, Elizabeth, d. 1665 --  Anecdotes.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Cookery, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:56650:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56650:1"/>
            <p>THE COURT &amp; KITCHIN OF <hi>ELIZABETH,</hi> Commonly called <hi>Joan Cromwel,</hi> THE Wife of the late Usurper, Truly Described and Represented, And now Made Publick for general Satisfaction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho. Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourn,</hi> for <hi>Randal Taylor</hi> in St. <hi>Martins Le Grand,</hi> 1664.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:56650:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56650:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HAT there may no prejudice lye against this Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication, as an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sultory, unman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Invective and Triumph over the supposed miserable, and forlorn estate of this Family, and this Person in particular; it will be requisite to obviate &amp; prepare against that seeming humane (but indeed disloyal, or at least idle) sentiment and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the frail and flu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuating
<pb facs="tcp:56650:3"/>condition of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, which as a general Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument is ready at hand to oppose the design of the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suing Treatise.</p>
            <p>Not to refer the Reader to the practise of all Times, which have not sailed to wreak the fury of the Pen upon Tyrants and Usurpers (if surviving to punishment, otherwise their Relations and Posterity) whose execrable Tragedies have wearied the World, and blunted the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struments of death &amp; slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: nor to instance the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular examples thereof, as sufficient Authority for this Imitation; the peculiar Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice due to the monstrous e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>normities
<pb facs="tcp:56650:3"/>and unparalle'ld in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solence of these upstarts, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides the disproportion and imcompetence of any revenge to their provoking impudent personation of Princes) will interessedly vindicate and defend the Author from the breach of charity, much more from the rigid imputation and charge, as of a person de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vested and void of nature, compassion and civility.</p>
            <p>For while they yet wanton in the abundance of their spoyl &amp; rapine, afflicted with nothing else but the torments of ambitious designs, taking this cloud upon them, but as an Ecclipse of their former Greatness, and as but a Turn
<pb facs="tcp:56650:4"/>of <hi>sporting</hi> Fortune, whose wheel may with an imaginary volutation roll their pretty Highnesses upwards again; how can the desperate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed estate of many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand loyal Subjects, who are irrecoverably lost and past all means, but a miracle, to their just, or any competent Resti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution, or to buoy up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves or Families from vulgar or Phanatick contempt: How is it possible for them to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port with the Serenity (instead of disaster) of this Family, by whose single accursed plots and designs, all their present and many more grievous past miseries are derived upon them and their Posterity.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:56650:4"/>
            <p> And that this may not seem the froth and spleen of a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr, what meaneth that bleat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their present stately Mansions? The same ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious and respectful obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, as if they were still the <hi>Hogen Mogens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>None of the Family must presume to speak less than my Lord and my Lady, to the Squire <hi>Henry</hi> and his Spouse, and the same stile is used when ever any mention is made of them in the House<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold; to which pin the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and necessary Retainers addresses are tunably raised. What is this but to strengthen their weak, yet vain-glorious fancy, and to preserve some
<pb facs="tcp:56650:5"/>reliques of their former vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, lest rude and inoffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous time should plead a disu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ser in bar to their conceited (but airy) reversion? And no question but the old Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman, who took so much upon her, and was so well pleased with her last Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur, as displeased and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted with the fall of it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Fleetwood, Richard</hi> and <hi>Desborough,</hi> is also served in the same manner, and with the same Grandezza's, so that such is the inveterate itch and tetter of Honour in Her, that nothing but the lees of gall, and the most biting sharpest Ink will ere be able to cure or stop this <hi>Protectorian Evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:56650:5"/>
            <p> And herein we do but reta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liate (if they be not unworthy of such a term, as that any attribute of justice should be profaned by their demerit which exacts rather popular Fury) and repay them in some sort, those many Libels, blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous Pamphlets and Pasquils, broached and set on foot, chiefly by the late U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surper, against the blessed Memory and Honour of our two late Soveraigns: more especially those vile and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious Pieces, called, <hi>The Court and Character of King</hi> James, and <hi>The None such</hi> Charles, (a great number of which were bought up in the juncture of the late Restitution, (as par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly informed) which in
<pb facs="tcp:56650:6"/>the worst of times their bold and impudent falshood made most abominable) were none of the least incentives to a work of this nature, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quital of that traiterous and most petulant Imposture.</p>
            <p>Whereas the guilt of this <hi>Grand-Dame</hi> hath this sort of felicity, that it cannot be made worse or more odious by any additions of devised untruths; and he must be a very immodest and immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Fabulist that can repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Her to greater disadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage in this way, then Her Actions have infamed her to the World.</p>
            <p>Her Highness must be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
<pb facs="tcp:56650:6"/>to dispense with this frank and libertine manner of treating Her, for 'tis all we are like to have for many millions; besides an old Saw or Proverb to the bargain,</p>
            <p>—<hi>Olim haec meminisse ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vabit;</hi> a little transitory mirth, for twenty years dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of sorrow; and if she thinks she comes not very well off so, she is as unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable in her reduction and allowed Recess, (to be envied for its plenty and amplitude, far exceeding her former pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacy, so that she is even yet a Darling of Fortune) as in her usurped Estate and Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness.</p>
            <p>It is well for her, if his <hi>Butche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:56650:7"/>(then, which the Sun never saw a more flagitious execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble fact, and so comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive, that it reached <hi>Caligulas</hi> wish) can be slighted into her <hi>Cookery;</hi> and that there were no other <hi>Monument</hi> of it then in <hi>Paste,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>— <hi>Ʋt tantum schombros metuentia Crimina, vel Thus:</hi> That the records of his Crimes were onely damn'd to an <hi>Oven.</hi> Little <hi>satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> serves the English Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (the Relations of those loyal persons martyred by Him excepted) and She ought therefore to be highly thankful, that the <hi>Scene</hi> of his <hi>Tyranny</hi> was laid here, for had it light upon the <hi>Southern parts</hi> of the World,
<pb facs="tcp:56650:7"/>their <hi>nimble</hi> and <hi>vindictive</hi> rage, upon the <hi>Turn,</hi> would have <hi>limb'd</hi> and <hi>minced</hi> her Family to <hi>Atomes,</hi> and have been their own <hi>Cooks</hi> and <hi>Carvers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lambert Simnel</hi> very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentedly turned a broach in the Kings Kitchin, after the Gaudies of his Kingly Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posture, in the beginning of the Reign of <hi>Henry</hi> the VII. and therefore for variety sake let this once mighty Lady, do <hi>Drudgery</hi> to the Publique.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Vale.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:56650:8"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56650:8"/>
            <head>The Introduction.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong all the mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strous Effects of <hi>Cromwell</hi>'s Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, and the fruition of his U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surped Greatnesse; in the affluence of all imaginary delights to gratify his sense, and candy over the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of his mind (to the rendring them lesse severe and dulling their poignant acutenesse) it was by all men much wondred at, that he was so little guilty of any luxurious and Epicurean Excesses either in his meat or drink, except some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in his Cups, which he pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posely and liberally took off to void
<pb facs="tcp:56650:9"/>the Gravel in his Kidneys, with which he was continually molested, and for which, large draughts were his ordinary Cure.</p>
            <p>In this He differed from the rest of his sanguinous Tribe and sort of men, who making use of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane blood for their drink, do sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginate and fatten themselves, with the superfluous variety of meats, to whose natural satisfaction such artificial devices are added (even retorturing the Creature) that the genunine Gusto is quite changed by this adulteration, and lost in the mixt multiplicity of other Relishes and palatable Ingredients. Herein like themselves, when not content with their natural private condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of life, and the pure results &amp; simple innocent delights there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, they do corrode their minds with the sharp sawces of Ambition,
<pb facs="tcp:56650:9"/>and so alter and invert their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that they degenerate to other things, and become such a <hi>quel. que-chose</hi> of villany and debau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery, that we can hardly sever and distinguish a Crime which is not intervitiated with many other. And what prodigious infamy upon this gulose and intemperate ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, and by this very apt simili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude doth this day stick upon many if not most of the <hi>Roman</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors! as I could instance in <hi>Tibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius, Caligula, Nero, Otho, Domitian, Commodus, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racalla, Heliogabolus,</hi> men not to be mentioned without horrour at their wickednesse; of such savage and feral manners, as if their food had been the flesh of <hi>Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Tygers</hi> and <hi>Bears,</hi> and had assimilated its nutriment in their Bestial qualities: but as was
<pb facs="tcp:56650:10"/>said before, <hi>Cromwell</hi> as in some other cases, was in this wholly <hi>discriminated</hi> from them.</p>
            <p>Yet do I not think this abstemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse and temperance was due only to his disposition either of body or mind, for his appetite in all other things was very irregular &amp; inordinate, but either to the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of those <hi>mordaces &amp; eda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Curae,</hi> biting and eating cares and ambitious thoughts; which made him either the Vulturs or <hi>Tantalus</hi> his Feast, and were his continual Surfets of <hi>an evil con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science;</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>Districtus Ensis cui super impia</l>
                  <l>Cervice pendet, non Siculae dapes</l>
                  <l>Dulcem elaborarint saporem.</l>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Horat. Od</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q> though I may indulge his military labours and discipline, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample
<pb facs="tcp:56650:10"/>that severer abstinence: or else which is principally inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded here as the Subiect matter of this discourse, it may be cheaplyer referred to the sordid frugali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and thrifty basenesse of his Wife, <hi>Elizabeth Bowcher,</hi> the Daughter of Sir <hi>James Bowcher,</hi> commonly called Protectresse <hi>Joan</hi> and vulgarly known of later years by no other Christian name, even in the greatest Heighth of her Husbands power, and that chiefly out of Derision and contemptuous indignation, that such a person durst presume to take upon her self such a Soveraign Estate, when she was an hundred times fitter for a Barn then a Palace; so sporting, mocking Fate, to make good that of the Satyrist
<q>
                  <l>Foelix à Tergo quem nulla Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conia pinxit,</l>
               </q>
               <pb facs="tcp:56650:11"/>followed her great luck with that Sarcastick and dicterious nick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>name, that she with her Copemate might perceive, their Fortune was not so entire and of so fair an aspect and firm Structure, but that the Flaws and Blemishes and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potence thereof, were most obvious and ridiculous; their Fine Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers had Swans feet, and their beautiful Mermaid, the fiction of Dominion, had the ugly tail and fins of a Fish, the <hi>Train</hi> of her greatnesse and prosperity was the most vile and scornful reproaches. And this shall suffice to be spoken of her person by way of Preface, the next Elenchus or Discourse is of her Mesnagery Huswifery or House keeping.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:56650:11"/>
            <head>THE COURT <hi>and</hi> KITCHIN OF Mrs. ELIZABETH alias <hi>Joane Cromwell.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>TO Confine and limit this Treatise to its purpose and designment prefixed in the Title, we must (though with some petty injury to the Reader) pass over her Oeconomy at her private home, before <hi>Olivers</hi> bold atchieve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and attainment of the Supreme power, (because part of it is already
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:56650:12"/>publique) when she had brought as (we say) a <hi>Noble to Nine-pence,</hi> by her pious negligence and ill manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Domestique Affairs, and was as giddy to see her bare Walls as <hi>Oliver</hi> was mad with <hi>Enthusiasmes</hi> and Devinations of Regal Furniture and all Princely pomp and greatness. Those Memorials may be reduced to this present use in this short Corolla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the former Extremities of her Necessitous and indigent Condition, upon the bettering thereof (by the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Ruine) raised in her such a quick sense of the misery of want, that she became most industriously pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident, and resolvedly sparing and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious for the future, and to prefer the certainty of her own care and diligence to the extempore, fond and easie delusions of</hi> Deus providebit, <hi>with which she had been fooled before into an almost voluntary and devoted poverty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This her Aspect and Consideration of the future, extended it self (with more prudence and sagacity then her
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:56650:12"/>Husband would descend to) in some humble thoughts of her present rise levelled to her past depression: She took a prophetical prospect of the Times, and having seen two, three or four variations in the calmnesse and tranquility of her Husbands For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, did wisely presage to her self that after those Hurly burlies of war and the Tempest of Rebellion, wherein he had whirled, and with so much impatient precipitancy engaged himself, there would another turn happen, against which she conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be more <hi>discreetly Armed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The first Eddy of that boysterous and unruly Current of his Prosperity, which at last over-ran all Banks and Boundaries flowed into the recepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of her Committee-ship in the associated Counties, particularly <hi>Cambridge</hi> and <hi>Huntingdon,</hi> where to recover and peice up her ruines, she with the same Spirit of zeal and piety of her Husbands, consecrated her House to be the Temple of <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine,</hi> one of the prime Goddesses
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:56650:13"/>next the <hi>Cause;</hi> whither for sacrifices all manner of Cattel clean and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean, were brought from all the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jacent parts; as other costly uten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sils of the best moveables to adorn and enrich this sacred place; from whence to hope for any re-delivery was mental Sacriledge, and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devour it was punished with irrepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ruin; and I am sure (like the guilt of that crime) there are some who now feel it to the third generation, and may without miracle to perpetuity.</p>
            <p>For not only was her <hi>Corban</hi> to be satisfied with the product of such oblations, but lands were to be set a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part and sequestred, the revenue of which past first through her fingers, and were made Impropriations of her own.</p>
            <p>Having thus recruited her Estate, and adjusted her present Seizures to her past losses, and exalted above the Dignity of Mrs. Sheriff, or Countesse of those Shires, no person her equal in greatnesse; upon the Successe of her Husband after <hi>Marston Moore</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:56650:13"/>she abandoned the dull Country, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly not enduring the ordinary demean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or of her acquaintance towards her, nor sufferable nor endurable by her betters, for her imperious and unso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciable Carriage towards all persons of quality; and partly to partake in the supreme Fruition of the City's more elaborate &amp; exquisite pleasures, &amp; to huswife early admiration: for the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of the Cause began to appear at Thanksgiving dinners, and to reckon as many dishes to a Messe, as their Husbands numbred atchievements.</p>
            <p>At her Arrival in Town she was little lesse then saluted by the whole Juncto, though not in a body, yet severally by them all, and afterwards by the Pastours, Elders, and Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of the Sects, who came not a House warming with the breath of their Mouths, in zealous gratulations, but brought all Silver Implements for her accommodation of housh old stuff, and offered them according to the late pattern of Reformation in <hi>Guild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hast.</hi> Nor did this humor cease here,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:56650:14"/>the middle sort of the Religiously Phanatique, sent her in <hi>Westphalia Hams, Neats Tongues, Puncheons,</hi> and <hi>Teirces</hi> of <hi>French Wine, Runlets</hi> and Bottles of Sack; all manner of Preserves and Comfits, to save her the trouble of the Town; the most of which gifts, they being multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon her, she retailed by private hands, at as good a rate as the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket would afford.</p>
            <p>But much more of these was given afterwards when <hi>Oliver</hi> was returned from the ending the war, and was lookt upon as the great Motion of the Parliaments proceedings: not to reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on those immoderate Bribes that ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truded themselves upon her, more welcome by far then those saintlike benevolences and civil Offices of Love, under which their corrupting practices were vailed to no purpose; for she very well understoood the very first Addresses though never so innocently remore from the main de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign, and would rate them (as they do Post Miles, for she kept her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:56650:14"/>distant Stages in all her publique Brocage and Transactions) duely and exactly.</p>
            <p>And indeed her House was in this respect a Political or State <hi>Exchange</hi> by which the Affairs of the Kingdom were governed, and the prizes of all things set, whether Offices, prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Indempnity; as all other manner of Collusion and Deceipts were practised, and money stirring no where else: And in the other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of <hi>Provisions,</hi> it might have pass'd for the Temple of <hi>Bell</hi> and the <hi>Dragon,</hi> (to persue the former San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctity of her Rural Mansion) where all those offerings of Diet were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumed, or as good, altered and assimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated to her nature (the use of the nutritive faculty) by serving her Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetousnesse in their reduction to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney.</p>
            <p>Now she needed no such austere diligence in the preservation of an estate, for it was more then she and her Ministers could do to receive it. It was impossible to keep any Deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:56650:15"/>or order, in that house where ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterlesse money like a haunting Spirit, possessed and disquieted every room. It was a kind of <hi>Midas</hi> his Palace, where there was nothing but Gold to eat, only instead of being confined to that indigestible food, she and her Servants were most frequently invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out of Dores to most sumptuous and magnificent treatments, whence because of that more sacred employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at home, (like Sabbatarians that provide themselves bak'd and cold meats for the superstitious obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the day) they and their progging Lady brought home such re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques, as they might mumble down in the dispatch of their businesse, and save the trouble or Magick of their long Graces, which had brought a curse instead of a Blessing, upon their Masters and Mistresses first en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devours, though she her self (so hard it is to foregoe and shake off an habitual customary Hypocrisie and falacy) would look as religiously upon a Match pane, Preserve, or Comfit,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:56650:15"/>as a despairing Lover upon his Mistresses Lips.</p>
            <p>But the War expired, and those Thanksgiving and triumphal Festivals over and ended, this pious family be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to enter upon the years of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine after those of Plenty. Her Husband was now engaged in deep designes and practices upon the King and Kingdome, and in order to ruin them both, upon the Army; Every one of those mischievous and Matchiavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian consultations and projects, were ushered continually by a Fast, which being appointed for, and observed by the Host, were always intimated to the friends and Relations of the Officers, and kept by them with no lesse strictnesse in their private hous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds; which by the frequent shifts, and various turns of policy, which <hi>Cromwell</hi>'s Fate, and the uncertainty of the Times guided him to, came so often and thick upon the neck of one another, that her Domesticks had almost forgot dinner time; up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>start
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:56650:16"/>Piety, like the modern Frugali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, bating a Meal, and as that had li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited the diet to Noon, this changed it and inverted it to night.</p>
            <p>So that, as in other authoritative continued Fasts, there is a political and humane Reason, <hi>viz.</hi> the sparing the Creature, even to the same end, this good Huswife directed her do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mestick abstinence; and when on such occasions she had cause to suspect a general discontent of her people and houshold; she would up with this Scripture expression, and lay it in their Teeth for better fare; <hi>The Kingdome of God is not Meat and Drink, but Righteousnesse and Peace,</hi> and some such Scriptural dehortations from gluttony and the like luxuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Intemperance, and other zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Sentences of Moderation in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et; as that the pleasure of a full diet consists more in desire then in Satie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; that to have the Stomach twice repleated in the day, is to empty the Brain, and to render the mind un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serviceable to the actions of life;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:56650:16"/>No Abysse, no Whirlpool is so per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious as Gluttony, which the more a man eats, makes him more a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry; and the better he dines to sup the worse, with such other Morals, taken out of <hi>Gusman</hi> and <hi>Lazarillo de Tormes,</hi> and only altered a little, by being made serious in practice.</p>
            <p>Yet I cannot passe this necessary Lesson of Temperance, however it proceeds from this Sophistical cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Teacher thereof, without some reflection on some more ancient and authentique Instructions, but because it is a little beside my design, I will conclude them in some fit Sentences, as of the Satyrist <hi>Persius.</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>Poscis opem nervis Corpusque fidele Senectae,</l>
                  <l>Esto age sed grandes patinae tucetaque crassa</l>
                  <l>Annuere his superos vetuere Jovemque morantur.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:56650:17"/>
            <p> Englished thus,
<q>
                  <lg>
                     <byline>
                        <hi>By</hi> De Barten Holyday.</byline>
                     <l>Thou wishest for firm nerves, and for a sure</l>
                     <l>Sound body, that would healthfully endure</l>
                     <l>Until Old Age; why be it, that thy wish</l>
                     <l>Is granted by the Gods; yet thy large Dish</l>
                     <l>And full fat sasage make the Gods Delay</l>
                     <l>To blesse thee, and do Force good <hi>Jove</hi> to stay.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And that other of <hi>Epictetus,</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be inscribed in all our Parlours and Banquetting-Houses, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. In another place <hi>Inter Epulandum duos excipere debe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Convivas,</hi> Corpus &amp; Animam; <hi>Tum quod in Corpus collatum sit repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te effluxurum, quod autem in animam perpetuo servandum (i. e.)</hi> in Feasting and banquetting we must except two Guests the body and the mind, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause that which is bestowed on the body will suddenly passe away, and that which comes into the mind will be there laid up for ever; adding that commendation of <hi>Plato</hi> to a friend a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:56650:17"/>Philosopher; <hi>Vestrae quidem caenae non solum in praesentia sed etiam postero die sunt jucundae,</hi> intimating that there is no such lasting pleasure as in a sober diet, which, when Excesses bring Surfeits, renews the Feast the next day, and gives a continual relish to the Appetite.</p>
            <p>But I must beg pardon for this (o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise seasonable) digression, and reduce the Discourse in purfuit of her Ladyships Errantry from one abode to another, in the Suburbs of <hi>London,</hi> more or lesse like a Sojourner, (how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever she inhabited whole Houses) and a great person <hi>incognito,</hi> then as a Woman of that State and degree, to which her Husbands Condition and Command, and great probabilities of succeeding Titles, and forespeak her; If any thing could be observe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by her for state and charge, it was the keeping of a Coach, the driver of which served her for Caterer, as much occasion as she had for him, for Butler, for Servingman, for Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman Usher, when she was to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:56650:18"/>in any publtque place. And this Coach was bought at the second hand, out of a great number, which then lay by the Walls, while their honourable owners went on foot, and ambled in the dirt to <hi>Goldsmiths</hi> and <hi>Haberdashers-halls</hi> if so fairly come by. She might, and she did ('twas thought) save that very inconsidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Charge, but the sense she had how obvious and odious her Carriage in a sequestred Caroach would be to every body, made her jealous of such scorn and derision; as for Horses she had them out of the Army, and their Stabeling and Livery in her husbands allotment out of the <hi>Mews,</hi> at the charge of the State; so that it was the most thrifty and unexpensive pleasure and divertisement; (besides the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nery and Honour of it) that could be imagined; for it saved many a Meal at home, when upon pretence of businesse, Her Ladyship went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, and carrying some dainty provant for her own and her Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters own repast, she spent whole days
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:56650:18"/>in short visits, and long Walks in the Ayre; so that she seemed to affect the <hi>Scythian</hi> fashion, who dwell in Carts and Wagons, and have no other habitations.</p>
            <p>Her publique Retinue was also ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry slender, and as slenderly accou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, no more commonly, then one of her Husbands Horse boys running by her, sometimes one, and some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times another; with or without Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, all was one; on purpose (it may be well supposed, beside the saving the Cost) to prevent her being dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryed and discovered, so much suspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion &amp; hatred had her husband drawn upon himself, even from the vulgar which she feared, might by some such Badge of notice, light upon her self in the streets as she passed.</p>
            <p>She was the same <hi>recluse</hi> likewise in her Habit, rarher <hi>harnessing</hi> her self in the <hi>defence</hi> of her Cloaths, then allowing her self the loose and open bravery thereof, as not having been used to such <hi>light armour;</hi> and her Hood, till her face was seen in her
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:56650:19"/>Highnesses Glasse, was clapt on like a <hi>Headpiece,</hi> without the Art of <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sconcing</hi> and <hi>entrenching</hi> it double and single in <hi>redoubts</hi> and <hi>hornworks.</hi> In fine, she was <hi>Cap a pe</hi> like a <hi>Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage</hi> Lady, and was out of her Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in her vicinity to the Court and City.</p>
            <p>But her Daughters were otherwise vested and robed, and a constant ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence allowed in Tire-women, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumers, and the like Arts of Gallan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, with each their Maid and Servant to attend them: and by their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ray and Deportment, their quality might have been guessed at; they were all (those that were unmar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried) very young; but Mrs. <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> who about this time was mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to one Mr. <hi>Cleypole</hi>'s Son of <hi>Northamptonshire</hi> (the old man ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving had a hand in the same disloyal Service with <hi>Oliver,</hi> in that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) but with a very private Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, no way suitable to that Port and Grandeur, which <hi>Oliver</hi> kept in the Army, where he was look'd
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:56650:19"/>upon with the same reverence and respect as the General himself; all that was <hi>Hymen</hi> like in the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of it, was some-freaks and pranks without the Aid and Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of a Fidler (which in those days was thought by their precise Parents to be altogether unlawful and sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring of Carnality, as the ring and form of Marriage, were thought superstitious and Antichristian) in <hi>Nol</hi>'s military rude way of spoyling of the Custard, and like <hi>Jack Pud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> throwing it upon one another, which was ended in the more manly Game of buffetting with Cushions, and flinging them up and down the room.</p>
            <p>Neither appeared there the Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor and Ornament of Jewells, and Pearls, and the like Lusture of Gems, whose invidious refractions like pov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonous Effluxes, might invenome the World with Spleen and Malice, at their plundered and stollen radiancy; for by the manifold Surrenders and Stormings of Houses and Castles,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:56650:20"/>
               <hi>Cromwell</hi> had amassed good store of rarities, besides Meddals, and gold and silver Vessels, (the spoyls of our Captivity) which it was not as yet safe to produce in such an unsettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Conquest, till all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety should be hudled up in the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral ruine, out of whose mixt and confused rubbish, in his new pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ish'd Covernment, they might ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ert their Brightnesse underivable and clear from all former title and claim, as the Masse of things shall be mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and calcined together, at the last uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versal Dissolution.</p>
            <p>And I have heard it reported for a Truth, that most of the precious moveables, and other things of value, at the storming of <hi>Basing-house</hi> by <hi>Cromwell,</hi> fell into his hands either immediately or directly, the Soldiers either by Command, or for some smal price returning several precious pei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the spoyle, whose worth they understood not, to his Agents, who gave an exact Account thereof to the Lady Receiver at home, who was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:56650:20"/>that time seen to be very plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant and prajeant at the enjoyment of those pretty things (as she express'd her self) being the best for substance and ornament, that belonged to the noble Marquiss of <hi>Winchester</hi> and his Family, which this she-Usurper now listed and Catalogued for her own.</p>
            <p>And if the whole Inventory of her rapinous hoard were now producible, what a Voracious Monster would she appear to be? not a Corner in the Kingdome which is not sensible of her Ravage, and which had not a share in the Lombard of her uncountable and numberless Chattels.</p>
            <p>How many rare peices of antique Gold and Silver, are again damned to the earth from whence they were brought? and are by her mischievons Covetousnesse irrecoverably lost, which have been the glories and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numental pride of many Families? and the only remains and evidences of their noble Hospitality, now buried by this Wretch in hugger mugger.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:56650:21"/>
            <p> Those advantages, together with the vails of the Army, which she had upon every Commission, and other incident occasions, for her Husbands Interests and Authority, together, with his Extraordinary pay, and the Appurtenances to it, and Lands, and Hereditaments bestowed on Him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides rewards and gratuities in ready money, amounted to an incredible Sum, which almost glutted her eyes to satiety, but so, that they were yet lesser then her belly, which could stow as much more with conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence enough, and conserve and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure it by a very parcimonious use, and narrow strict Disbursement; for having now quitted all Fears of returning to a private condition by the insolence of her Husbands For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, which drove at the Soveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the abhominable design being communicated to her; this great bank was still kept supplied by her, for the support and maintenance of that Dignity and Supremacy to which <hi>Oliver</hi> aspired, and to facilitate his
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:56650:21"/>way to it; having rightly perceived, that nothing but mony had carried on the War, and brought things to that passe, whatever was pretended of Zeal, and to the Cause, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there was no difference in her manner of Housekeeping, only <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> being now in Town for the most part, conspiring that execrable Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricide against the King, she dispensed with her niggerly Regulation, and having taken a House neer <hi>Charing-Crosse,</hi> kept it in a manner open for all Comers, which were none but the <hi>Sectary</hi> party and Officers, who resorted thither as to their head-quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, with all their wild projections, and ere entertained with <hi>Small Beer</hi> and <hi>Bread and Butter,</hi> which to the animation of the approaching Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, was as bad as <hi>Aqua fortis</hi> and <hi>Horse Flesh:</hi> for as was said of <hi>Caesar, Nemo tam sobrius ad Rempublicam evertendam accessit, no man came more sober to the destruction of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth;</hi> so I may aptly and more justly say, That no men of more ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stemiousnesse
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:56650:22"/>ever effected so vile and flagitious an enterprise upon so just a Government.</p>
            <p>That being in perpetration, Mrs. <hi>Cromwell</hi> ran out of Purse some score of pounds, (for it is to be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred that she Stewarded it all along, <hi>Oliver</hi>'s head being busy with greater and worser matters) very much to her regret and vexation; but that Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny over; and some two or three pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Treatments given his most sure and addicted Complices, in Exalta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their monstrous Successe; the dores of the house were again bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and all persons hindered, and of dissicult admittance, upon what score or businesse soever; and now she was returned to her former privacy, and ordinary Diet as be sore.</p>
            <p>During the rest of the time while <hi>Cromwell</hi> staid in <hi>England,</hi> she kept the same tenour, having received (besides a Confirmation of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiss of <hi>Worcester</hi>'s Estate, to the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of <hi>five thousand pounds</hi> a year) upon the account of the defeat given
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:56650:22"/>Levellers by her Husbands Treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry at a Thanksgiving dinner (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to he was invited by the City) a piece of Gold Plate of very good value, which discharged the former Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence.</p>
            <p>I must omit many other passages during his absence in <hi>Ireland</hi> and in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and after this liminary, but prolix Account, sum up all in her menage of her Domestique Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> for which she had so long prepared and furnisht her self with Rules of Government and Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conomy, fitted for her Usurpation and the Times.</p>
            <p>For her Husband brought not so great and haughty, as she base and low spirited thoughts and resolutions to the grandeur of that place, the Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation and Residence of the greatest and most famous Monarchs of the World, and famed throughout it for truly Royal and Princely Pomp, and immense Munificence and Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:56650:23"/>
            <p> She had flesh enough indeed to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come any room in that spacious Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, but so little of a brave Spirit, that the least Hole of it would have made her a Banquetting House; but like a Spirit she came only to haunt, not to enjoy any part of it; The <hi>Penates</hi> and <hi>Genii</hi> of the place ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominating this prophane and sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legious Intrusion, neither giving him one hours quiet or rest in it, from his troubled, mistrustful, and ill boding thoughts, nor her any Content and Satisfaction, but what she found in repining &amp; vexing her self at the cost and Charge, the maintenance of that beggerly Court did every day put her to.</p>
            <p>It was in the year 1653, that <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> first possessed and seated himself there, as in his own right, and in Chief, and brought his Worshipful Family thither, to their several ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partiments, she having appointed one Mr. <hi>Maidstone</hi> to be Steward of his House, and one Mr. <hi>Starkey</hi> to be his Master Cook (who afterwards
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:56650:23"/>was betrayed and taken drunk in his Cellar, designing the like upon my Lord Maiors Sword-bearer, while my Lord was in Conference with the Protector, so that he could not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal it from the Houshold, who (out of spight to Him, as being a spie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their Actions and behaviours) first acquainted their Lady, and she <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi> with the fault, aggravated by the Scandal and wastful Excesse; inso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, that <hi>Starkey</hi> was comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to come before him, where in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stead of a Complement and Excuse, He delivered himself by Vomit, in the very Face of his Master, and was thereupon dismissed the House.</p>
            <p>It will not be too distant a Review to observe and remarque her Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction to, and Seizin of this Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Mansion, (which we have only mentioned) before any other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedure in the Oeconomy thereof.</p>
            <p>The first Preparatory as to publique notice, was an Order from the new Council of State, after the dissolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Parliament, command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:56650:24"/>all persons to depart out of <hi>White-hall,</hi> which was then the Den of a hundred several Families, and persons of power, and office in the Anarchy; which being difficultly and grumblingly executed, she her self employed a Surveyor to make her some convenient accommodati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and little Labyrinths, and trap Stairs, by which she might at all times unseen, passe to and fro, and come unawares upon her Servants, and keep them vigilant in their places, and honest in the discharge thereof.</p>
            <p>Several repaires were likewise made in her own appartiments, and many small partitions up and down, aswel above Stairs, as in the Cellars and Kitchins, so that it looked like the Picture of <hi>Bartholomew Faire;</hi> Her Highnesseship, not being yet ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>customed to that roomy and August Dwelling, and perhaps afraid of the vastnesse and silentnesse thereof, which presented to her thoughts the Desolation her Husband had caused, and the dreadful apparitions of those
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:56650:24"/>Princes, whose incensed Ghosts wandred up and down, and did at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend some avenging opportunity; and this was the more believable, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause she (not to name her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands mis-giving Suspicions and Frights) could never endure any Whispering, or to be alone by her self in any of the Chambers.</p>
            <p>And it is further here fit to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stanced, that upon her first coming, when her Harbingers had appointed her Lodgings, the same with the Queens, which yet retained their Royal Names and Distinctions, she would by no means hear of them but changed them into other Appellati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that there might remain no man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of disgust and discontent to her ambitious and usurping Creatnesse: and therefore they were adapted now into the like significations, by the name of the Protectors and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectresses Lodgings, as more proper and fitter terms to their propriety, and indisputed possession.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:56650:25"/>
            <p> Much adoe she had at first to raise her mind and deportment to this So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Grandeur; and very difficult it was for her to lay aside those im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent Meannesses of her private fortune; like the Bride-cat by <hi>Venus's</hi> favour metamorphosed into a comly Virgin, that could nor forbear cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching at Mice, she could not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port with her present Condition, nor forget the common converse and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of Life; but like some Kitchin Maid preferred by the Lust of some rich and noble Dotard, was ashamed of her sudden and gawdy bravery, and for a while skulkt up and down the House, till the fawning obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances and reverences of her Slaves had raised her to a Confidence, not long after sublimed into an impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</p>
            <p>And this was helped on by Madam <hi>Pride,</hi> and my Ladies <hi>Hewson,</hi> and <hi>Ferkstead, Goff, Whalley,</hi> &amp;c. who all came to Complement her High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse upon the Felicity of <hi>Cromwell</hi>'s Assumption to the Government, and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:56650:25"/>to congratulate her Fortune, and so accompany her to her Palace of <hi>Whitehall,</hi> where like the Devil <hi>cast out,</hi> she <hi>entred</hi> by <hi>Fasting</hi> and <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> after the usual manner, and like devout <hi>Jezabel,</hi> took possession of <hi>Naboth</hi>'s Vineyard.</p>
            <p>And thus we have waited on her to this <hi>Basilicon,</hi> now swept and clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed for her <hi>fiendly</hi> entertainment; and the Chymneys smoked and heated a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, which had suffered so long a <hi>damp;</hi> and after so long a Vacation; Especially her Highnesse took care, and gave strict charge to have all the rooms <hi>aired,</hi> for fear of those ill Sents the <hi>Rump</hi> had left behind them and was willing to be at the charge of Perfumes to expel the noysomenesse thereof, the account of which hath been seen by divers, allowed by her own hand; but foul odour was so e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually natural to all the Grandees, that <hi>Oliver</hi> when he died left it in a worse condition then when he found it, as is publique in several Treati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:56650:26"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Cromwell</hi> was now his own Steware and Carver, not limited to any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences of Housekeeping, no more then to the Charges of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; but was absolute both at Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and at Council Board, neither of which were yet well setled; And therefore, besides the nearness of his Wife, it was necessary he should ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear extraordinary frugal of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Purse, (who wish'd every bit he eat might choke him, for all his temperance) in his private and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Disbursements. Only that he might not appear so much a Military Governour, but have something of the Prince in him, about Noon time, a man might hear a huge clattering of Dishes, and noise of Servitors, in rank and File marching to his Table, (though neither sumptuously nor ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarily furnished) in some imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of <hi>Paulus Aemilius</hi> in his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer to the <hi>Grecians,</hi> after his Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph and Conquest or <hi>Perseus,</hi> the last <hi>Macedon</hi> King; <hi>Ejusdem esse A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimi &amp; Aciem &amp; Convivium instrue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ere,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:56650:26"/>illam quidem ut formidolosus Hostibus hoc ut Amicis gratus appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reat;</hi> in English thus, <hi>'Tis of the same spirit to order a Battle, as to furnish a Feast, by the one a man ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears terrible to his Enemies, and by the other pleasing to his Friends.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But at his private Table, very rarely or never, were our <hi>French quelque-choses,</hi> suffered by him or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny such modern <hi>Gusto's,</hi> whether with the Fright he was prejudiced of Poyson, by such devices, (at an vitation made him and his General the Lord <hi>Fairfax,</hi> with the other of the supreme Commanders of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, by a small Officer therein, who was formerly a Cook) at a Ladies in <hi>Hammersmith,</hi> where with one Leg of Mutton drest all sorts of ways he entertained them all, but upon their discovery of the Fellowes audacious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse in bidding them, which promp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them to believe it was a design a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst their lives, and put most of them to the Vomit, was like to have been drest himself by the Hangman)
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:56650:27"/>or by some stronger or more Mascu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line Appetite, which partaked with his other robust faculties, is uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain; sure it is, that when in Treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments given his Familiars, such things were set upon the Table, 'twas more for shew and sport then for Belly Timber, and about which the good Huswife never troubled her head.</p>
            <p>She, to return to her Government, very providentially kept two or three Cowes in St. <hi>James's</hi> Park, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected a new Office of a Dairy in <hi>Whitehall,</hi> with Dairy Maids to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend that businesse solely, (as most of the Employment for Servants was managed by Females, for there were no Sergeants but such as waited with Halbeirds on the Guard) and fel to the old Trade of cherming But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and making Buttermilk, nor were <hi>Oxford Kates</hi> find things, half so famous among the Cavalier La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, as my Lady Protectors Butter among the Mushrome zealous La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of the Court, most whereof, being Apple, or Oyster-women, or
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:56650:27"/>Stocking-Heelers, and the like, did much wonder at, and magnifie the invention and rarity.</p>
            <p>Next to this Covy of Milk Maids she had another of Spinsters, and Sowers, to the number of six, who sate the most part of the day, after she was ready, in her privy Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber sowing and stitching; they were all of them Ministers Daughters, such as were inveterate Nonconformists to the Church, for which cause, and the pretence of piety (the main in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredient to things of the least Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) they were added to the Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; Nor did the Turkish Ministers take more care to furnish the <hi>Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glio,</hi> and gratifie their Master with choice Virginities, then some of these pious Pimps did lay out for indigent godly Maidens to pleasure this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitute Charity of hers, that the world might take notice of her exemplary Humility and Compassion. But in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed all persons of breeding and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, abhorred the indignity of her Service, and so rather then be ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:56650:28"/>with common Drudges, she e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected this new order, and continued it to the term of her Usurpation. Herein following the Steps of her Husband, who made a new daring Militia of zealous persons, since he could not be served with generous Spirits.</p>
            <p>She was once resolved by the As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance and Advice of her Mother, to have made a small brewing place, with Vessels, and other accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation for her own, and <hi>Oliver</hi>'s Drink, as not liking the City Brew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, nor trusting to the Artifices of the Town; but about the same time, a Drink was then grown famous in <hi>London,</hi> being a very small Ale of 7 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi> a Barrel, well boyled, and well tasted and conditioned, called, and known by the name of <hi>Morning Dew</hi> (from the Brewers name as I haue heard) which was thence brought into request at Court, and vvas the Diet Drink of this temperate Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and the cool refreshing enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment of those bouncing Ladies
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:56650:28"/>that came vveltring and vvallovving in their Coaches instead of Drayes to visit Her.</p>
            <p>And for the Kitchin and Pantry a great Reformation was intended, but the multitude of Comers and Goers upon her first setling there, and num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Mouths which came gaping for preferment, being to be stopt with Victuals, put her besides her proposed Regulation, yet was there not a joynt of Meat for which the Cook was not to give an account, which she overlook'd, as it came from them to the Steward, whose ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts likewise were punctually cast up by her, and firmed by her hand, aswell as afterwards by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectors.</p>
            <p>Nay, so severe and strict she was in this thrifty way of House-keeping, that she descended to the smallest and meanest matters, the very Chaffer, and price of the Market, and that the Reader may not think he is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed on and deceived by a general imputation of her niggardlynesse: I
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:56650:29"/>will give him two notable and appo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>site instances.</p>
            <p>The first, was the very next Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer after his coming to the Protecto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate in 1654. in <hi>June,</hi> at the very first season of Green Pease, where a poor Country Woman living some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where about <hi>London,</hi> having a very early but small quantity in her Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, was advised to gather them, and carry them to the Lady Protect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resse, her Counsellors conceiving she would be very liberal in her reward, they being the first of that year; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly the poor Woman came to the <hi>Strand;</hi> and having her Pease amounting to a Peck and a half, in a Basket, a Cook by the <hi>Savoy</hi> as she passed, either seeing or guessing at them, demanded the Price, and upon her silence offered her an Angel for them, but the Woman expecting some greater matter, went on in her way to <hi>Whitehall,</hi> where after much adoe, she was directed to her Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and one of her Maids came out, and understanding it was a Present
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:56650:29"/>and Rarity, carried it in to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectresse, who out of her Princely Munificence sent her a Crown, which the Maid told into her hand; The Woman seeing this basenesse, and the frustration of her Hopes, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring withal what the Cook had proffered her; <hi>threw back the money into the Maids hands, and desired her to fetch her back her Pease, for that she was offered five shillings more for them before she brought them thither, and could go fetch it presently;</hi> and so half slightingly and half ashamed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, this great Lady returned her pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent putting it off with a censure upon the unsatisfactory daintinesse of luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and prodigal Epicurisme: The very same Pease were afterwards sold by the Woman to the said Cook, who is yet alive to justifie the truth of this Relation.</p>
            <p>The other is of a later date, upon <hi>Oliver</hi>'s Rupture with the <hi>Spanyard,</hi> the Commodities of that Country grew very scarce, and the prizes of them raised by such as could procure
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:56650:30"/>them underhand: Among the rest of those goods, the fruits of the growth of that place were very rare and dear, especially <hi>Oranges</hi> and <hi>Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One day, as the Protector was pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate at dinner; He called for an <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range</hi> to a Loyne of Veal, to which he used no other Sauce, and urging the same command, was answered by his Wife, <hi>that Oranges were O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranges now, that Crab Oranges would cost a Groat, and for her part, she never intended to give it;</hi> and it was presently whispered, that sure her Highness was never the adviser of the <hi>Spanish</hi> War, and that his Highness should have done well to have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sulted his Digestion, before his hasty and inordinate appetite of Dominion and Riches in the <hi>West Indies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I might confirm this by other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenchments of Expence, whensoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver she could confine his Table to her own privacy; particularly it was a great Mode, and taken-up by his Court party to roast half Capons,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:56650:30"/>tending a more exquisite tast and nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triment in it, then when dressed whole and entire; where I cannot but smile to think how it purzzled her Ladyships Carver, to hold him to the Knife, and to apportion half and quarter Limbs according to Art.</p>
            <p>Much more do I wonder what those Fellows at <hi>Rome</hi> did, or what they would have done here, who kept carving Schools <hi>ludi structorii,</hi> and had all manner of Fowl and Fish, and such other grand Festival meat carved in Wood, which they marked out with wooden Knives with very great curiosity, and instructed their Scholars, who learned it as a worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Employment and way to prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as the Satyrist very elegantly.
<q>
                  <l>Sumine cum magno lepus atque aper &amp; Pygargus,</l>
                  <l>Et Scythicae volucres, &amp; Phoenicop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terus ingens,</l>
                  <l>Et Getulus Oryx hebeti lautissima Ferro</l>
                  <l>Caeditur, &amp; tota sonat ulmea caena sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urra.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:56650:31"/>
            <p>Englished thus,
<q>
                  <l>The Sow's large Teat, the Hare and Bore and Deer,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Scythian,</hi> &amp; <hi>Africks</hi> Fowl and Bearded Beast,</l>
                  <l>The Gawdies of the Town, in Wood appear,</l>
                  <l>So with dull Iron carv'd sounds Elmy Feast.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And if it were not made almost incredible by the Superfluity and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse of her fortune, which cannot be supposed to have no way advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced her thoughts from her former in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustry, and frugal care and inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency.</p>
            <p>I might insert a story of her en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry into the profit of the Kitchin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stuff, and the exchanging of it for Candles, which those that knew her humour had purposely put into her head; till she was told to whom it belonged; and the Customes of the Court, to most of which she an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered, they should not think to have
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:56650:31"/>them take place as in the <hi>other Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans dayes,</hi> for she would look bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to it: like <hi>Vespasian,</hi> she had learnt, That <hi>Dulcis odor lucri ex re qualibet,</hi> Gain was sweet from what ever thing.</p>
            <p>And the reason she used to give for this her frugal Inspection and Parcimony, was the small allowance and mean pittance she had to defray the Houshold Expences, which at her first coming to Court keeping, was barely sixty four thousand pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> until Collonel <hi>Philip Jones,</hi> came to be Comptroller of the Hous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, when the weekly charge was Nineteen hundred twenty three pounds odd money, the defalcation of the rest, from the just sum of two thousand pounds, at the rate of a 100000 <hi>l.</hi> yearly, making up the four thousand pound for the two Weeks, above the 50. so exactly was this charge computed, and method punctually observed, that there might be no place for Excesse, and by means thereof, for deceit or any col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luding practises.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:56650:32"/>
            <p> Her order of Eating and Meal times, was not lesse regulated, and though inverted, yet designed well to the decency aswell as conveniency of her Service; for first of all, at the ringing of a Bell dined the Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berdiers, or men of the Guard with the inferiour Officers; then the Bell rung again, and the Stewards Table was 9set (in the same Hall neer the Water Stairs) for the better sort of those that waited on their Highnesses; Ten of whom were apportioned to a Table or Messe, one of which was chosen by themselves every week for Steward, and he gave the Clerk of the Kitchin the Bill of Fare, as was agreed upon generally every morning: To these Ten men, and what Friends should casually come to visit them, the value of 10. shil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings in what flesh or fish soever they would have, with a Bottle of Sack, &amp; two of Claret, was appointed; but to prevent after Comers from expecting any thing in the Kitchin, there was a general rule, that if any man thought
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:56650:32"/>his businesse would detain him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond dinner time, he was to give notice to the Steward of his Messe, who would set aside for him as much as his share came too, and leave it in the Buttery.</p>
            <p>Suppers likewise they had none, Eggs or some slaps contenting <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> and her Ladyship and to his exemplar all was conformed; in lieu thereof, for the Family there was constantly boyled 8 Stone of Beef early in he morning, to keep her Retainers in heart and in earnest of a dinner, the Broth whereof, and all he Scraps and Reliques of din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, (to give her her due) were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternately given to the Poor of Saint <hi>Margarets Westminster,</hi> and Saint <hi>Martins</hi> in the Fields, according to the Churchwardens Roll of each Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish, and that very orderly, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Brabble or noise; so that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midst so many Curses and imepreca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which were uttered against him; he had some Prayers and Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings from those hungry <hi>Jack Dawes,</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:56650:33"/>that frequented and attended this <hi>Dole.</hi> But those lame, decrepit, and starved precepts, never reached half way, and like impotent suspended Meteors, hoysed half Region high, fell distinctly at last upon himself and Family.</p>
            <p>His Feasts was none of the libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallest, and far from magnificence, even those two he gave the <hi>French</hi> Embassador, and the Parliament in 1656, upon their gratulation of his <hi>Syndercombe</hi> deliverance, which last amounted not to above 1000 <hi>l.</hi> and she saved 200 <hi>l.</hi> of it in the Banquet, for a Big Bellied Woman, a Spectator, neer <hi>Cromwell</hi>'s Table, upon the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving thereof with Sweatmeats; desiring a few dry Candies of Apricocks, Col. <hi>Pride</hi> sitting at the same, instantly threw into her Apron a Conserve of Wet, with both his hands, and stain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it all over; when as if that had been the Sign, <hi>Oliver</hi> catches up his Nap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin and throwes it at <hi>Pride,</hi> he at him again, while all of that Table were engaged in the Scuffle: the noise
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:56650:33"/>whereof made the Members rise be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Sweat-meats were set down, and believing dinner was done, goe to this pastime of Gambols, and be Spectators of his Highnesses frolicks. Were it worth a Description, I could give the Reader a just and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Account of that <hi>Ahab</hi> Festi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val, as it was solemnized in the Banquetting House of <hi>Whitehall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I must passe it, and those other Nuptial Entertainments at the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of his Daughters, and the Treats he gave to Duke <hi>De Crequi;</hi> and Monsieur <hi>Mancin</hi> the Cardinal's great Counsellors, and Familiars Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew, as things beyond her Sphere, and out of her charge and my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, and instance the common or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary diet of this Family, whereby the Reader will better perceive, and be perhaps advantaged also by the intention and nature of this Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="collection_of_recipes">
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:56650:34"/>
            <head>Here follows the most usual Meat and Diet observed at her Table, most of them ordinary and vulgar, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept some few Rarities, but such as arrided her Palate and Expence, of which it will be no un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleasing Labour to the Keader, to peruse the <hi>Cookery,</hi> and manner of Dressing, as also her Preserves, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:56650:34"/>
               <head>How to make a Rare <hi>Dutch</hi> Pudding.</head>
               <p>TAke a pound and a half of <hi>Fresh</hi> Beef, all lean, take a pound and a quarter of Beef Suet, sliced both very small, then take a half penny stale Loaf and grate it, a handful of Sage, and a little Winter Savory, a little Time, shred these very small; take four Eggs, half a pint of Cream, a few Cloves, Nutmegs, Mace and Pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per finely beaten, mingle them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together very well, with a little Salt, roll it all up together in a green Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort Leaf, and then tye it up hard in a Linnen Cloth, garnish your Dish with grated bread, and serve it up with Mustard in Sawcers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:56650:35"/>
               <head>How to roast a Leg of Mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton the French way.</head>
               <p>Take half a pound of Mutton and a quarter of a pound of Suet, sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son it with sweet Heaths, and a little Nutmeg, and two or three Shallots; slice these very small, and stuff the Mutton round, then take some of the best <hi>Hackney</hi> Turnings, and boyl them in Beef Broth very tender, then squeeze the water from them a little, set them in a Dish under the Leg of Mutton when it is half roasted and so let the gravy drop into them, and when the meat is roasted serve them in the Dish with it, with a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Fresh Butter and Vinegar, garnish your Dish with sliced Onions and Parsley, and some of the Turnip sliced.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:56650:35"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>How to make Scotch collops of Veal.</hi> (this was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most Her constant Dish.)</head>
               <p>Take a Fillet of Veal, cut it out into very broad slices, fat and leau, not too thick; take eight Eggs, beat them very well with a little salt, grate a whole Nutmeg, take a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of Thyme and strip it, take a pound of Sawsedges, half a pint of Stewing Oysters, the largest to be had, wash and cleanse them from the Gravel: then half fry your Veal with sweet Butter, then put in your Sawsedges and Oysters, then take a quarter of a pouud of Capers, shred them very small; three Anchovis, dissolve them in white Wine and fair water, so put in your Eggs, shred Capers, and Anchovis, Butter and Spice, and mingle them, and strew
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:56650:36"/>them in the Pan upon the Vealand Oysters; serve it with Sippets, with a little fresh butter, and vinegar, and Limons sliced, and Barberies, with a little salt. You must have a care to keep the meat stirring, lest the Eggs curdle with the heat of the fire.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>How to souse a Pig and col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar it like a Brawn.</head>
               <p>After you have stuck the Pig let him bleed well, then with scalding water and Rozin finely beaten take off the Hair, let him lye in gold wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a little space, shifted two or three times, that he may look white, then cut off the Feet, flit him open, and take out his inwards, and cut off his head, take the two sides asunder, lay them in cold water, steep it there a day and a night, shifting the water thrice, then take out the bones, toll up each side several, tying them as hard as possible, in the fashion of a Collar of
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:56650:36"/>Brawn, then tye it up in a Cloth hard, and put the head whole in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, then boyle it in water and Salt, Cloves, Mace, and Nutmeg, and a handful of <hi>Rosemary,</hi> and ome Sweet herbs, while it is very tender; take it up and let it cool, then put it into the liquor that boyled it, adding there to two quarts of Small Beer; set the two Collars in a Dish garnished with Salt, (with the head entire in the middle) and stick in two Sprigs of Rosemary flowred and serve it with Sawcers of Mustard.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>How to make a Sweet Pye with Lamb-stones, and Sweet-breads, and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar.</head>
               <p>Take the Lambstones and slit them in the middle, and skin them, wash the Sweatbreads both of Veal and Lamb, and wipe them very drye,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:56650:37"/>take the Lambs Liver and shred it ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry small; take the Udder of a Leg of Veal and slice with it, season all with a little salt, Nutmeg, Mace, and Cloves beaten, and two whole Pepper, then shred two or three Pippins and candid Limon and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range peel, half a dozen dates sli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, with Currants and White Sugar, a few Carroway seeds, a quarter of a pint of Verjuice, and as much Rosewater; a couple of Eggs; Roll up all these together in little pud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of Balls made green with the juice of Spinnage, and lay a pudding, then a Sweatbread, and then a Lamb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stone, till you have filled up the Pye, and cover them with Dates and sliced Citron and Limon. When it is drawn take two or three Yelks of Eggs, beat them, and put them to a little fresh Butter, White wine, and Sugar, and pour it into the Tunnel, scrape some Loaf Sugar upon the Lid and so serve it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:56650:37"/>
               <head>A rare White-pot.</head>
               <p>Take three pints of Cream, whole Cinamon, a little sliced Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meg, set on the Cream, and spice and scall'd it, take a penny Loaf slice it very thin, take a Couple of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row bones, lay the Marrow sliced on the bottome of the Dish, upon the Marrow lay the bread, then lay Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sins of the Sun over the bread, and lay Marrow again as before, to the 3. pints of scalded Cream add 9 Yelks of Eggs well beaten, with Rose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water, sweeten the Cream with white Sugar, and take out the whole Cinamon, and beat the Cream and eggs well, fill up a broad shallow Basin, and bake it; when 'tis e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough scrape fine Sugar on it, and stick it with red and white Muska-does, and so serve it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:56650:38"/>
               <head>A rare <hi>Citron</hi> Pudding.</head>
               <p>Take a penny Loafe and grate it, a pint and a half of Cream, half a dozen of eggs, one Nutmeg sliced, a little Salt, an Ounce of candied Citron sliced small, a little candied Orange Pel sliced, 3 Ounces of Sugar, put those into a wooden Dish well flowered and covered with a Cloth, and when the water boyleth put it in; boyl it well, and serve it up with Rose-water and Sugar, and stick it with Wafers or blanch'd Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>How to make Liver Pud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings.</head>
               <p>Take the Guts of a young Hog, wash them very clean, and lay them two or three dayes in the water, take the Liver of the same Hog and boyle
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:56650:38"/>it till it will grate, then grate it very small and fine, take to the weight of the Liver almost the weight of Beef Suet, season it with Salt, Cloves, Mace, and Nutmeg, finely beaten, a penny Loaf grated, a pound of the best white Sugar, two pound of good Currants, a pint of good Cream a quarrer of a pint of Rose water, three eggs; mixe altogether to such a thicknesse as you may fill the Guts, then prick them, and put them into boyling water, and keep an even sire for half a quarter of an hour, then take them up and lay them upon straw; you must have a care in boyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, that you <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ye them not too hard nor too slack, less they break.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:56650:39"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>How to make Marrow Pud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings,</hi> (which she usu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally had to her Break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fast.)</head>
               <p>Take a pound of the best Jordan Almonds, blanch them, beat them fine in a stone or wooden Mortar (not in brasse) with a little Rose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water, take a pound of fine powder Sugar, a penny Loaf grated, grated Nutmeg, a pint of Cream, the Marrow of two Marrow-bones, two grains of Ambergris; mingle them altogether with a little Salt, fill the Skins, boyl them gently as before.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>How to make Marrow Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties.</head>
               <p>Take some Marrow and Apples,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:56650:39"/>shred the Marrow and Apples, and put to them a little Sugar; put them into puff past, and frie them in a pan with fresh butter, and serve them up to the Table with a little white Sugar strowed in it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>A Country way to make Sawsedges.</head>
               <p>Take Pork, not so much sat as lean, mince it exceeding small to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, then take part of the Fleck of Pork, which is the suet, in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces about the bignesse of the top of your finger, season each apart with minced Sage, good store of Pepper and Salt, some Cloves and Mace, mixe in the seasoning into each of them; take the small sheeps Guts, and cleanse them, (other use Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pors Guts) and fill them with your Funnel, always putting some of the Fleck between the minced, if you have it ready you may sprinckle a
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:56650:40"/>little Sack on the top of the Sawsedge Meat, it will make it fill the better.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>Another way.</head>
               <p>Cut a Gammon that is very red, and half boyl it, mince it very small, if the Gammon be not fat, take half as much Lard of Bacon, mince it likewise, mingle them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and beat them in a Mortar, season it with Time and Sage minced very small, and good store of Pepper beaten to dust, with a little Cloves, Mace, and Nutmeg, and a pretty quantity of Salt, for they must tast of that very strong, add to them the Yolk of two Eggs, and so much red wine as will bring them up into a stiff body, mingle them well with your hands, fill them into middle Skins as big as ordinary Sawsedges, then hang them in the Chymney for a time, they are not to be eaten in the Skin, but must be cut out very thin roundways, and do serve for Sallet all the year long.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:56650:40"/>
               <head>To make green Sawce.</head>
               <p>Take a handful, or a greater quantity of Sorrel, beat it in a Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar with Pippins pared and quarte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, add thereto a little Vinegar and Sugar, put it into Sawcers. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise take Sorrel, beat it and stamp it well in a Mortar, scruze out the juice of it, put thereto a little Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negar, Sugar, and two hard eggs minced small, a little Butter and grated Nutmeg, set this upon the Coals till it is hot, and pour it into the dish on the Sippets, this is Sawce for hen, or Veal and Bacon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To dresse Ʋdders and Tongues.</head>
               <p>When they are boyled enough in the Beef Pot and skinn'd, you must have your Turnips ready boyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:56650:41"/>cut in peices and soakt in Butter, or otherwise Collyflowers and Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rets, or all of them, then put the Turnips all over the bottome of a large dish, then slice out the Tongues and lay the sides one against another, slice the Udders and lay them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween, opposite to one another, garnish the Collyflowers all over them, and the Carrets up and down between the Collyflowers, with Barberies and Parsley in the brim of the dish.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To make Goosberry Cream.</head>
               <p>First boyle, or you may preserve your Goosberries, then having a clear Cream boyled up and seasoned with old Cinamon, Nutmeg, Mace, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, Rose-water and Eggs, dish it up, and when it is cold take up the Goosberries with a pin, and stick them on in rounds as thick as they can lye upon the said Cream, garnishing
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:56650:41"/>your Dish with them, and strow them over with the finest Sugar and serve them up.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To make Punnado.</head>
               <p>Take one quart of running water, put it on the sire in a Skiller, then cut a light Roul of bread in slices, about the bignesse of a groat, and as thin as Wafers, lay it on a dish on a few Coals, then put it into the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with two handful of Currants, pickt and washt, a little large Mace, season it with Sugar and Rosewater, when it is enough.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To make a Sack Posset.</head>
               <p>Set a Gallon of Milk on the fire, put therein whole Cinnamon and large Mace, when it boyls stir in a half or whole pound of Naples bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket grated very small, keeping of it stirring while it boyls, then beat S.
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:56650:42"/>Eggs together, casting of the whites away, beat them well with a Ladle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of Milk, then take the Milk off the Fire and stir in the Eggs, then put it on again, but keep it stirring for fear of curding, then make rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy a pint of Sack, warming it upon Coals with a little Rose water; sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son your Milk with Sugar, and pour it into the Sack in a large basin, and stir it apace, then strow on a good deal of beaten Cinnamon, and so serve it up.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To make a made Dish of Apples.</head>
               <p>Put on a Skillet of water with some Currants a boyling; then pare about a dozen of Pippins, and cut them from the Core into the said water, when they are boyled tender, pour them into a Cullendar, when the water is drained from them, put them into a dish and season them
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:56650:42"/>(but if you have time stay until they are cold, lest it melt your Sugar, besides it will spoil the Tast) with Sugar, Rose-water, Cinnamon, and Carraway-seeds, then roll out two sheets of past; put one in the Dish bottome, and all over the Brims, then lay in the Apples in the bottom round and high, wet it round and cover it with the other sheet; close it and carve it about the brims of the Dish as you please, prick it and bake it, scrape Sugar upon it and serve it up.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To roast Eels.</head>
               <p>Shen they are flead, cut them to peices about three or four inches long, drye them, and put them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Dish, mince a little Time, two Onions, a peice of Lemmon Pill, a little Pepper beaten small, Nutmeg, Mace, and Salt, when it is cut ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding small, strow it on the Fels with the solk of two or three Eggs,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:56650:43"/>then having a small Spit (otherwise a couple of square sticks made for that purpose) spit through the Eele cross wayes, and put a bay Leaf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween every peice of Eele, and ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the sticks on a Spit let them roast. You need not turn them constantly, but let them stand until they hisse, or are brown, so do them on the other side, and put the dish (in which the Eele was with the seasoning) under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath to save the gravy, bast it over with sweet Butter. The sawce must be a little Clarret Wine, some min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Oysters with their liquor, a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Nutmeg and an Onion, with sweet Butter, and so serve it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To make an Eele Pye.</head>
               <p>Your Eeles being flead, washed, and cut in pieces, as long as you think convenient, put to them a handful of sweet herbs, Parsley minced with an Onion, season them with Pepper, Salt, Cloves, Mace,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:56650:43"/>and Nutmeg, and having your Cos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sin made of good past, put them in and strew over them, two handful of Currants, and a Limon cut in slices, then put on Butter and close the Pye, when it is baked, put in at the Funnel a little sweet Butter, white Wine and Vinegar, beaten up with a couple of Yolks of Eggs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To dresse a <hi>Cods</hi> head.</head>
               <p>Cut off the Codds head beyond the Gills, that you may have part of the body with it, boyl it in water and salt, to which you may add half a pint of Vinegar, the head must be little more then covered before you put it into the Caldron, take a quart of the biggest cleanest Oysters, and a bunch of sweet hearbs and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and put them into the mouth of the head, and with a packthread bind the Jawes fast, you must be sure to pick it and wash it very clean, when it is boyled enough, take it up
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:56650:44"/>and set it a drying over a Chafingdish of Coals, then take the Oyster Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor, four Anchoves, and a sliced Onion; put to them a quarter of a pint of white Wine, and sweet but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and melt them together, and pour it on the Cods head, stick all or most of the Oysters upon the head, or where they will enter, and garnish it over with them, grate on a little Nutmeg, and send it smoking up, garnish the brims of the dish with Limon and sliced bay Leaves.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To boyle Perches.</head>
               <p>Let your Liquor boyle, and your Pan be seasoned with a little white Wine, a couple of Onions cut in halfs, and a bunch of sweet hearbs, and a little white Pepper, boyl them up very quick, and flea them on both sides, and dish them upon Sippets, then take a little white Wine, gravy, and Vinegar, with a grated Nutmeg, and almost boyl it over a Chafing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dish,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:56650:44"/>then pour sweet Butter over it; garnish it with Barberies and sliced Limmons.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To boyle Eeles.</head>
               <p>Cut the Eeles as before, and stew them, when they are half done, beat a little Ale with Vinegar, and put into the Liquor, with some Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sley and sweet hearbs: Dish them and serve them up in their broth with a little Salt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To boyle Woodcocks or Snipes.</head>
               <p>Boil them either in strong broth, or in water and salt, and being boyled take out the Guts and chop them small with the Liver, put to it some crumbs of grated whitebread, a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of the Broth of the Cock, and some large Mace; stew them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:56650:45"/>with some gravy, then dissolve the yolks of two Eggs with some wine Vinegar, and a little grated Nutmeg, and when you are ready to dish it, put the eggs to it, and stir it amongst the sauce with a little Butter; dish them on sippets, and run the sauce o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them with some beaten Butter, and Capers, or lemon minced small, barberies or whole pickled grapes.</p>
               <p>Sometimes with this sauce boile some slic't onions, and currans boil'd in a broth by it self; when you boil it with onions rub the bottome of the dish with Garlick.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>How to boil Cocks or Larks otherwayes.</head>
               <p>Boil them with the Guts in them, in strong broth, or fair water, and three or four whole onions, large mace, and salt; the Cocks being boil'd, make sauce with some thin slices of Manchet of grated bread in
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:56650:45"/>another Pipkin, and some of the broth where the fowl or the cocks boile, then put to it some butter and the guts and liver minced, then have some yolks of eggs dissolved with some Vinegar, and some grated nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meg, put it to the other ingredients, stir them together, and dish the fowl on fine sippets, pour on the sauce with some slic't lemon, grapes, or barberies, and run it over with bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten butter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To boile Capons, Pullets, Chickens, Pigeons, Phea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sants or Partridges.</head>
               <p>Fearce them either with the bone or boned, then take off the skin whole, with the legs, wings, neck, and head on, mince the body with some bacon or beef-suet, season it with nutmeg, pepper, cloves, bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ginger, salt, and a few sweet herbs finely minced and mingled among
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:56650:46"/>some 3 or 4 yolks of eggs, some su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, whole grapes, goosberries, barbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and pistaches; fill the skins and prick them up in the back, then stew them between two dishes with some strong broth, white wine, butter, some large Mace, marrow, goosberries, and sweet herbs; being stew'd serve them on sippets with some marrow and slic'd lemon; in winter, cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To boil a Chicken or Capon in White Broth.</head>
               <p>First boyl the Capon in water and salt, then take three pints of strong broth, and a quart of white wine, and stew it in a pipkin with a quarter of a pound of dates, half a pound of fine sugar, four or five blades of large mace, the marrow of 3 marrow bones, a handful of white endive; stew these in a pipkin very leisurely, that it may but only simper, then being
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:56650:46"/>finely stew'd and the broth well tast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, straim the yolks of ten eggs with some of the broth. Before you dish up the Capons or Chickens, put in the eggs into the broth, and keep it stirring that it may not curdle, give it a walm and set it from the fire; the fowle being dished up put on the broth, and garnish the meat with dates, marrow, large mace, endive, preserved barberies, and oranges, boil'd skirrets, poungarnet, and curnells. Make a lear of almond paste and grape verjuyce.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>A Turkish dish of meat.</head>
               <p>Take an interlarded piece of Beef, cut it into thin slices, and put it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a pot that hath a close cover, or stewing pan; then put into it a good quantity of clean picked rice, skin it very well, and put into it a quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:56650:47"/>of wnole pepper, two or three whole onions, and let this boile very well, then take out the onions, and dish it on sippets, the thicker it is the better.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To stew a Fillet of Beef in the <hi>Italian</hi> Fashion.</head>
               <p>Take a young tender fillet of beef, and take away all the skins and sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>news clean from it, put to it some good white wine (that is not too sweet) in a boul, wash it and crush it well in the wine, then strow upon it a little pepper, and a poulder cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Tamara</hi> in <hi>Italian,</hi> and as much salt as will season it, mingle them ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vvell, and put to it as much white wine as will cover it, lay a trencher upon it to keep it down in a close pan with a weight on it, and let it steep two nights and a day; then take it out and put it into a pipkin with some good beef broth, but put
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:56650:47"/>none of the pickle to it, but onely beef broth: and that sweet, not salt; cover it close, and set it on the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, then put to it a few whole cloves and mace, and let it stew till it be enough, it will be very tender and of an excellent taste; serve it with the same broth as much as will cover it.</p>
               <p>To make this <hi>Tamara,</hi> take two ounces of coriander seed, an ounce of anniseed, an ounce of fennel seed, two ounces of cloves, and an ounce of cinamon; beat them into a gross powder, with a little powder of winter savory, and put them into a viol glass to keep.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To make an excellent Pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage called Skinke.</head>
               <p>Take a leg of beef, and chop it into three peices, then boil it in a pot with three pottles of spring wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, a few cloves, mace, and whole
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:56650:48"/>pepper; after the pot is scummed, put in a bundle of sweet marjoram, rosemary, time wintersavory, sage and parsley, bound up hard, some salt, and two or three great oni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons whole; then about an hour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore dinner put in three marrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bones, and thicken it with some strained oatmeal, or manchet slic't and steeped with some gravy, strong broth, or some of the pottage: then a little before you dish up the Skinke, put into it a little fine poulder of Saffron, and give it a walm or two; dish it on large slices of French Bread, and dish the marrow-bones on them <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a fine clean large dish; then h<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>o or three manchets cut into to<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>nd being finely toasted, lay <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>e knuckle of beef in the midd<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of the dish, the marrow bones round about it, and the toasts round about the dish brim, serve it hot.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:56650:48"/>
               <head>To stew a Rump, or the fat end of a Brisket of Beef in the French fashion.</head>
               <p>Take a Rump of Beef, boil it and scum it clean, in a stewing pan or broad mouthed pipkin, cover it close and let it stew an hour; then put to it some whole pepper, cloves, mace, and salt, scotch the meat with your Knife to let out the gravy, then put in some Clarret wine, and half a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen of slic'd Onions; having boil'd, an hour after put in some Capers, or a handful of brome buds, and half a dozen of Cabbidge lettice being first parboil'd in fair water, and quarter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, two or three spoorfuls of wine vinegar, and as much verjuice, and let it stew till it be tender; then serve it on sippets of French bread, and dish it on those fippets; blow off the fat clean off the Broth, or scum it, and stick it with fried bread.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:56650:49"/>
               <head>To boil a Chine, Rump, Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loine, Brisket, Rib, Flank, Buttock, or Fillet of Beef powdered.</head>
               <p>Take any of these, and give them in summer a weeks powdering, in winter a fortnight, stuff them or plain; if you stuff them, do it with all manner of sweet herbs, fat beef minced, and some nutmeg; serve them on brewis, with roots or cabbidge boil'd in milk, with beaten Butter, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To pickle roast Beef, Chine, Surloine, Rib, Brisket, Flank, or Neats Tongues.</head>
               <p>Take any of the foresaid Beef, as thine or fore-rib, and stuff it with
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:56650:49"/>pennyroyal, or other sweet herbs, or parsley minced small, and some salt, prick in here and there a few whole cloves, and rost it; then take Claret wine, wine vinegar, whole pepper, rosemary, and bayes, and time bound up close in a bundle, and boil'd in some Claret wine, and wine vinegar, make the pickle, and put some salt to it, then pack it up close in a Barrel that will but just hold it, put the pickle to it, close it on the head, and keep it for your use.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To stew Beef in Gobbets in the French fashion.</head>
               <p>Take a flank of Beef or any part but the leg, cut it into ssices or gob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bets as big as a pullets egg, with some gobbets of fat, and boil it in a pot or pipkin with some fair spring water, scum it clean, and put to it an hour after it hath boil'd, carrots, parsnips, turnips, great onions, salt, some
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:56650:50"/>cloves, mace, and whole pepper, cover it close, and stew it till it be very tender; then half an hour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore dinner, put into it some picked time, parsley, winter savory, sweet marjoram, sorrel and spinage (being a little bruised with the back of a ladle) and some claret wine: then dish it on fine sippets, and serve it to the table hot, garnish it with grapes, barberries, or gooseberries. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times use spices, the bottoms of boild artichocks put into beaten butter, and grated nutmeg, garnished with barberries.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>Stewed collops of Beef.</head>
               <p>Take of the buttock of beef thin slices, cross the grain of the meat, then hack them and fry them in sweet butter, and being fryed fine and brown, put them in a pipkin with some strong broth, a little cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret wine, and some nutmeg, stew it very tender; and half an hour before
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:56650:50"/>you dish it put to it some good gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, elder vinegar, and a clove or two: when you serve it put some juyce of orange, and three or four slices on it, stew down the gravy somewhat thick, and put into it when you dish it some beaten but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>Olines of Beef stewed and roste.</head>
               <p>Take a buttock of beef, and cut some of it into thin slices as broad as your hand, then hack them with the back of a knife, lard them with small lard, and season them with pepper, salt, and nutmeg; then make a sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing with some sweet herbs, time, onions, the yolks of hard eggs, beef-suet or lard all minced, some salt, barberries, grapes, or gooseberries; season it with the former spices lightly, and work it up together, then lay it on the slices, and soul
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:56650:51"/>them up round with some caul of veal, beef or mutton, bake them in a dish in the oven, or roste them, then put them in a pipkin with some butter, and saffron, or none, blow off the fat from the gravy and put it to them, with some artichocks, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tato, or skirrets blanched, being first boild, a little claret wine, and serve them on sippets, with some slic't orange, lemon barberries, grapes, or gooseberries.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To boil a capon or chicken with Colyflowers.</head>
               <p>Cut of the Buds of your flowers, and boil them in milk with a little mace till they be very tender, then take the yolks of 2 eggs, and strain them with a quarter of a pint of sack then take as much thick butter being drawn with a little vinegar and a slic't lemon, brew them together; then take the flowers out of the milk,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:56650:51"/>put them to the butter and sack, dish up your capon being tender boil'd upon sippets finely carved, and pour on the sauce, serve it to the table with a little salt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To boil a Capon or Chicken with Sparagus.</head>
               <p>Boil your Capon or Chicken in fair water and some salt, then put in their bellies a little mace, chopped parsley, and sweet butter; being boiled, serve them on sippets, and put a little of the broth on them: then have a bundle or two of sparagus boild, put in beaten butter, and serve it on your Capon or chicken.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>A rare Fricase.</head>
               <p>Take six pidegon and six chicken peepers, scald and trusse them being
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:56650:52"/>drawn clean, head and all on, then set them and have some lamb-stones and sweetbreads blanched, parboil'd and slic'd, frye most of the sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breads flowred, have also some as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paragus ready, cut off the tops an inch long, the yolks of two hard eggs, pistaches, the marrow of six Marrow-bones, half the marrow fryed green, and white batter, let it be kept warm till it be almost dinner time, then have a clean frying pan, and frye the fowl with good sweet butter, being finely fryed put out the butter, and put to them some rost Mutton gravy, some large fryed oy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, and some salt; then put in the hard yolks of eggs, and the rest of the sweetbreads that are not fryed, the pistaches, asparagus, and half the marrow: then stew them well in the frying pan with some grated nutmeg, pepper (a clove or two of garlick if you please) a little white wine, and let them be well stewed. Then have ten yolks of eggs dissol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedin a dish with grape-verjuice or
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:56650:52"/>wine vinegar, and a little beaten mace and put it to the frycase, then have a French six penny loaf slic'd into a fair large dish set on coals, with some good mutton gravy, then give the frycase two or three walms on the fire, and pour it on the sops in the dish; garnish it with fryed sweetbread, fryed oysters, fryed marrow, pistaches, slic'd almonds, and the juice of two or three Oran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To boil a Capon, Pullet, or Chicken.</head>
               <p>Boil them in good mutton broth, with mace, a saggot of sweet herbs, sage, spinage, marigold leaves and flowers, white or green endive, bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, bugloss, parsley, and sorrel, and serve it on sippets.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:56650:53"/>
               <head>To boil <hi>Capons</hi> or <hi>Chick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens</hi> with Sage and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sley.</head>
               <p>First boil them in water and salt, then boil some parsley, sage, two or three eggs hard, chop them; then have a few thin slices of fine man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chet, and stew all together, but break not the slices of bread, stew them with some of the broth where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Chickens boils, some large mace, butter, a little white wine or Vinegar, with a few barberies or grapes; dish up the chickens on the sauce, and run them over with sweet butter and lemon cut like dice, the peel cut like small lard, and boil a little peel with the chickens.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:56650:53"/>
               <head>To boil a <hi>Capon</hi> or <hi>Chick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en</hi> with divers composi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</head>
               <p>Take off the skin whole; but leave on the legs, vvings, and head; mince the body with some beef-suet or lard, put to it some sweet herbs minced, and season it with cloves, mace, pepper, salt, two or three eggs, grapes, goosberries, or barberies, bits of potato or mushrooms: In the winter with sugar, currans, and prunes fill the skin, prick it up, and stew it between two dishes, with large mace, and strong broth, pieces of artichocks, cardones or aspara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus and marrow: being finely stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, serve it on carved sippets, and run it over with beaten butter, le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on slic'd, and scrape on sugar.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:56650:54"/>
               <head>To boil a <hi>Capon, Chicken</hi> with <hi>Cardones,</hi> Mush<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rooms, Artichocks, or Oysters.</head>
               <p>The foresaid fowls being parboild and cleansed from the grounds, stew them finely; then take your car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dones being cleansed and peeled in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to water, have a skillet of fair Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter boiling hot, and put them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; being tender boild, take them up and fry them in chopt lard or sweet butter, pour away the butter, and put them into a pipkin, with strong broth, pepper, mace, ginger, verjuyce, and suyce of orange; stew all together with some stained al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds, and some sweet herbs chop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, give them a walm, and serve your capon or chicken on sippets.</p>
               <p>Let them be fearsed, and vvrap your fearst Fovvl in cauls of Veal,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:56650:54"/>half rost them, then stevv them in a pipkin vvith the foresaid cardonce and broth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To boil any Land Fowl, as Turky, Bustard, Phea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant, Peacock, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tridge, or the like.</head>
               <p>Take a Turkey and flay off the skin, leave the legs and rumps whole, then mince the flesh raw with some Beef suet or lard, season it with some nutmeg, pepper, salt, and some min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced sweet herbs, then put to it some yolks of raw eggs, mingle all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with 2 bottoms of boil'd Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chocks, rosted chesnuts blanched, some marrow, and some boil'd skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rets or parsnips cut like dice, or some pleasant pears, and yolks of hard eggs in quarters, some goosberries, grapes, or barberies; fill the skin, and prick it up in the back, stevv it
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:56650:55"/>in a stewing pan or deep dish, and cover it with another; but first put some strong broth to it, some Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rovv, artichocks boyled and quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, large mace, white wine, chesnuts qualters of pears, salt, grapes, barbeeries, and some of the meat made up in balls estewed with the Turkey; being finely boil'd or stewed, serve it on fine carved sip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, broth it, and lay on the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish with slices of lemon and whole lemon-peel, run it over with beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en butter, and garnish the dish with chesnuts, yolks of hard eggs, and large mace.</p>
               <p>For the lears or thickning, yolks of hard eggs strained with some of the broth, or strained almond paste with some of the broth, or else strained bread and sorrel.</p>
               <p>Otherwayes you may boil the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer fowls either boned and trust up with a farsing of some minced veal or mutton, and seasoned as the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer in all points, with those mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials, or boil it with the bones in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:56650:55"/>trust up. A Turkey to bake, and break the bones.</p>
               <p>Otherwayes bone the fowl, and fill the body with the foresaid farsing or make a pudding of grated bread, minced suet of Beef or Veal, sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soned with cloves, mace, pepper, salt and grapes, fill the body and prick up the back and stew it as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid.</p>
               <p>Or make the pudding of grated bread, beef-suet minced, some cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans, nutmegs, cloves, sugar, sweet herbs, salt, juice of spinage; if yellow, saffron, some minced meat, cream, eggs, and barberies: fill the fowl and stew it in mutton broth, and white Wine, with the gizard, liver, and bones, stew it down well, then have some artichock bottoms boil'd and quartered, some potatoes boil'd and blanched, and some dates quartered, also some marrovv boil'd in vvater and salt; for, the garnish some boil'd skirret or pleasant pears. Then make a lear of almond paste strained vvith mutton broth for the thickening of the former broth.</p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:56650:56"/>
               <p> Othervvayes simple being stuffed vvith parsley, serve it in vvith but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, vinegar, and parsley boiled and minced; as also bacon boiled on it or about it, in tvvo pieces, and tvvo saucers of green sauce.</p>
               <p>Or othervvayes for variety, boil your fovvl in vvater and salt, then take strong broth and put in a faggot of svveet herbs, mace, marrovv, cucumber slic't, and thin slices of interlarded bacon, and salt, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To boil <hi>Capon</hi> or <hi>Chicken</hi> with Sugar Pease.</head>
               <p>When the cods be but young, string them and pick off the husks; then take tvvo or three handfuls and put them int6o a pipkin vvith half a pound of svvet butter, a quarter of a pint of fair vvater, gross, pepper, salt, mace, and some sallet oyl: stevv them till they be very tender, and strain to them 3 or 4 yolks of eggs, vvith six spoonfuls of Sack.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:56650:56"/>
               <head>To make a Neats-Tongue Pye.</head>
               <p>TAke a couple of Neats Ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues and almost boyle them, then cut out the meat at the butt end, as far as you can, not break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it out at the sides, put a little suet to the said meat you cut out, a few sweet herbs and parsly ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led altogether very small, season it with a little pepper, salt, cloves, mace, ginger, and a handful of grated bread, a little sugar, and the yolks of three or four eggs, mould it up into a body, season your Tongues in the inside and outside with your seasoning afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, and wash them within with the yolk of an egge, and force them where you cut forth the meat, and make a forced meat of the residue; then having the coffin made in the form of a Neats Tongue, lay them in with the puddings little bales to them, put in dates and shred lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon with butter on the top, and
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:56650:57"/>close it up; when it is baked, put in a lear of the Venison Sawce, which is Claret Wine, a handful of grated bread, cinnamon, gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, sugar, and a little vinegar, boyl them up so thick, as it may onely run like butter, it ought to be sharp and sweet; this sawce serves for any part of Venison, wash'd the Shoulders, Sides and Hannches, which if seasoned, must be laid in water, and when roasted must be served up stuck with rose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To Roast a Levret or Hare.</head>
               <p>CAse your Levret, but cut not off their hinder legs nor ears, but hack one leg through another, so likewise cut a whole through one ear, and put it through the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; in the mean time make your Sawce with a little Tyme, Sweet-marjorum, and Winter-savoury very small, with the liver of the Hare boyled, and the yolks of three
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:56650:57"/>or four hard eggs, with a little Bacon and Beef-suet, boyl this well up with water and vinegar, when it is boyled, add a grated Nutmeg, sweet Butter, and a little Sugar, and dish your Hare; the same may you make to Rabbets.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To Stew Ducks the French fashion.</head>
               <p>TAke the Duck and half roast it, put half a score oynion; in the belly whole, some whole pepper, a bundle of tyme, a little salt, when it is half roasted, take it up and slash it into pieces, put it between two dishes, and pierce the gravy, mix some claret wine with that gravy, and a little sliced nutmeg, acouple of anchovies, wash them and slit them, slice the o-onyons in the Ducks belly, cover the dishes close, so let them stew while enough; take some butter, beat it thick and shred a lemmon in it and serve it, garnish your dish with the lemmon peel and your oynions</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:56650:58"/>
               <head>To make a Pidgeon Pie.</head>
               <p>TRuss your Pidgeons to bake, and set them, and lard the one half of them with Bacon, mince a few sweet herbs and parsly with a little beef suet, the yolks of hard eggs, and an onyon or two, season it with salt, beaten pepper, cloves, mace, and nutmeg, work it up with a piece of butter, and stuff the bellies of the Pidgeons, season them with some salt, beaten pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, cloves, mace, and beaten nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meg, take also as many lambs stones, seasoned as aforesaid, with six collops of Bacon, (the salt drawn out) then make a round coffin and put in your Pidgeons, and if you will put in lambs stones and sweet breads, and some arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choke bottoms, or other dry meat to soak up the juyce, because the Pye will be very sweet and full of it, then put a little white wine beaten up with the yolk of an egg
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:56650:58"/>when it comes out of the oven, and so serve it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To bouyl Pidgeons after the Dutch way.</head>
               <p>TAke your Pidgeons, set and lard them, put them into a pipkin with so much strong broth, (made of knucles of veal, and mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, and beaf) and well cover them, when they are scummed, put to them a faggot of sweet herbs, some large mace, a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of capers, and raisins of the sun shred very small, six quartered dates, a piece of butter with three yolks of hard eggs minced, with a handful of grapes or barbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, then beat two yolks of your eggs with verjuyce and some of white bread, a ladle of sweet butter &amp; a grated nutmeg, so serve it with sippits; though the modern way is to boyl it with colops of bacon, and dish it with rice boyled, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rets and turnips minced small and colliflowers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:56650:59"/>
               <head>To make an Egg Pye, or Mince Pye of Eggs.</head>
               <p>TAke the yolks of two dozen of eggs, shred them, take the same weight of beef suet, about a pound, half a dozen pippins, a poud of currants well washed and dried, half a pound of sugar, a penny worth of beaten spice, a few carroway seeds, candid orange peel shred, a little verjuyce, some rose-water, fill the coffin, and bake it with a gentle heat.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To make a Sallet of a cold Hen or Pullet.</head>
               <p>TAke a Hen and roast it, let it be cold, carve up the legs, take the flesh and mince it small shred a lemmon, a little parsley and ony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, an apple, a little pepper and salt with oyle and vinegar, garnish the dish with the bones and lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon peel, and so serve it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:56650:59"/>
               <head>To make a Hash of Capon or Pullet.</head>
               <p>TAke a Capon or Partridge and roast them, and being cold, mince them very fine, the brains and wings, and tear the leggs and rumps whole to be carbonadoed, then put some strong mutton broth or good gravy, greated nutmeg, a great onyon and salt, then stew them in a large earthen pipkin or sauce-pan, stew the rumps and legs in the same strong broth in another pipkin, then take some light French bread chipt, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the bottom of the dish, steep the bread in the same broth, or good mutton gravy, then pour the hash on the steeped bread, lay the legs and the rump on the hash, with some fryed oysters sliced lemmon, and lemmon peel, the juyce of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range, and yolks of eggs strained, and beaten butter, garnish the dish with carves oranges, lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, &amp;c. thus you may hash any
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:56650:60"/>kind of foul; there are other whimsical ingredients in the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Cookery, but I mention onely such as have a ready and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, not forced or forraign re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish, which was little used here.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To butter Eggs upon Toasts.</head>
               <p>TAke twenty Eggs, beat them in a dish with some salt, and put butter to them, then have two large Rolls or fine Manchets, cut them in Toasts and toast them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the fire with a pound of fine sweet butter, being finely butter'd in a fare clean dish; put the eggs on the toasts, and garnish your dish with pepper and salt, otherwayes half boyle them in the shells, then butter them, and serve them on toasts or toasts about them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:56650:60"/>
               <head>To Stew a Line, Leg, Breast of Mutton.</head>
               <p>TAke a loyn of Mutton and joynt it well, and do so to the breast, and draw and stuff it with sweet herbs and minced parsley, then put it in a deep stewing dish, with the right side downwards, put to it so much white wine and strong broth as will stew it, set it on a great heap of coals, put in two or three onyons, a bundle of sweet herbs, and a little large mace, when it is almost stewed, take a handful of spinnage, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sley and endive and put into it, at the last you may put some goos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berries or grapes; in the winter time sampiere and capers, here you may add them at any time, dish up the loyn of Mutton and put by the liquor you do not use, and thicken the other with yolks of eggs and sweet butter, so put on the sauce and the herbs over the
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:56650:61"/>meat, and garnish the dish with lemmon and barberies.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To hash a Rabbet.</head>
               <p>YOu must take the flesh from the bones of the Rabbet, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before washed, and mince it small with your mincing knife, so put to it a little strong broth and vinegar, an oynion or two, with a grated nutmeg, and set it stew up together, then mince a handful of boyled parsley green, with a lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon cut like dice, and a few bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berries, put it into the Harsh, and toste it altogether, and when it is enough, put a ladleful of sweet butter to it, and dish it upon the lines, so garnish it with lemmon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To Carbonado Mutton.</head>
               <p>BOyl a shoulder or breast of Mutton, then scorch them with your knife, and strew on minced tyme and salt, and a little
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:56650:61"/>nutmeg, when they are boiled, dish them up; the sauce is claret wine boyled up with two oynions, a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle famphiere and capers, and a little gravy, garnisht with lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To pickle Oysters.</head>
               <p>TAke a quart of the largest great Oysters, with the liquor, wash them clean, and wipe them, add to them a pint of fair water, with half a pint of white wine vineger, half an ounce of whole pepper, an handful of salt, a quarter of an ounce of large mace, with the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor of the Oysters strained, put altogether in a pipkin over a soft fire, let them simper together a quarter of an hour; when the Oysters are enough, take them up and put them into a little fair wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and vinegar, until they be cold, the pickle boyling a quarter of an hour after the Oysters are taken up, both being cold put them
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:56650:62"/>up together; when you use them, garnish the dish with barberries and lemmon, and a little of the mace and pepper, and pour in some of the pickle.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>Away to fry Rabbets with sweet sauce.</head>
               <p>CUt your Rabbet in pieces, wash it and dry it well in a cloth, take some fresh butter and fry the Rabbet in it, when your Rabbet is little more then half fryed, take some slices shred very small, a quarter of a pint of cream, the yolks of a couple of egges, some grated nutmeg and salt; when the Rabbet is enough, put them into the pan, and stir them alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, take a little vinegar, fresh butter and sugar, melt it together, and so serve it with sippets, the dish garnished with flowers, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:56650:62"/>
               <head>How to roast a Rabbet with oysters.</head>
               <p>WAsh your Rabbet and dry it well, take half a pint of Oysters, wash them and wipe them clean one by one, and put them into the Rabbets belly, a couple of oynions shred, whole pepper, large mace, two or three sprigs of tyme, sow up the belly: for the sauce as usual, the liver and parsley, a hard egge, shred them together, and beat some butter thick, put it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the dish and serve it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To make a Frickasse of Chickens.</head>
               <p>TAke three or four Chickens, scald them, flea off the skin and feathers together, put them in a little water, take halfe a pint of white wine, and two or three whole oynions, some large mace and nutmeg tyed up in a cloth, a bundle of sweet herbs and a little salt, and put them all in a pipkin
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:56650:63"/>closely covered, let them simmer a quarter of an hour, then take half a dozen yolks of eggs, half a pound of sweet butter, four anchovies dissolved in a little of the broth, shred your boyled spice small, take a quarter of a pound of capers, shred them very small, put the anchovies dissolved into the egges and butter and capers, and so stir it altogether over a chafing-dish of coals, till it begin to thicken, then take the Chicken out of the broth and pour lear upon them, serve them with sippets and lemmon sliced.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>Another way to fry the same Fricasse brown.</head>
               <p>TAke four Chickens, scald them and cut them in quarters, beat them flat with your cleaver, and break their bones, dry them with a cloth very well, and flower them all over on the skinny sides, your pan being hot with clarified but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:56650:63"/>put them in with the skinny sides downwards, fry them brown, then turn them, let your lear be a little claret wine and gravy, then put your liquor out of your pan, and put in your lear, with peices of sassages wrung off as long as your thumb, and a pint of oysters, two or three oynions, with a bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of sweet herbs, a grated nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meg, and two or three anchovies, let them boyl up in the pan, then beat the yolks of four eggs, with a little strong broth, take the pan off the fire and put them in, if it turns too thick, you may thin it with wine, gravy or strong broth, keep it shaking whilst it's on the fire; then dish up your Chickens in sippets, and pour on your lear and oysters, with your pieces of sassages by the sides of the dish, and garnish it with lemmon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:56650:64"/>
               <head>A grand Sallet.</head>
               <p>TAke a quarter of a pound of raisons of the sun, a quarter of a pound of blancht almons, a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of a pound of capers, a quarter of a pound of olives, the like quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of samphiere, a quarter of a pound of pickle cucumbers, a lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon shred, some pickled french beans, a wax tree set in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of the dish, pasted to the dish, lay all their quarters round the dish (you may also mince the flesh of a roasted hen, with sturgeon and shrimps) and garnish the dish with cut beans and turnips in se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral figures.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>How to pickle French-beans.</head>
               <p>TAke your Beans and string them, boyl them tender, then take them off, and let them stand till they are cold, put them into the pickle of beer-vinegar, pepper
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:56650:64"/>and salt, cloves and mace, with a little ginger.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>A Cordial strengthning Broth.</head>
               <p>TAke a red Cock, strip off the feathers with the skin, take a rolling-pin and bruise his bones to shivers, set it over the fire and just cover it with water, put in some salt, and watch the scumming and boyling of it, put in a handful of harts-horn, a quarter of a pound of blew currants, as many stoned raisins of the sun, as many prunes, four blades of large mace, a bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom crust of a white-loaf, half an ounce of china-root sliced, being steeped three hours before in warm water, boyl in three or four pieces of gold, strain it and put in a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle fine sugar and juice of orange and so use it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:56650:65"/>
               <head>Another way.</head>
               <p>TAke a Cock or two, cut off their wings and legs, cleanse all the blood out of the inside, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyl them very well, that when they are boyled, there may arise no scum, then wash them again in fair water, put them in a pitcher with a pint of Rhenish wine, and as much of your aforesaid strong broth as will cover them, add thereto a few cloves, large mace, shred ginger and nutmeg, a little whole pepper, with a small quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of china, and an ounce or two of harts-horn, put a little salt and stop up your pitcher close that no steam may come forth; you must boyl the pitcher in a great pot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout six hours, then pour out the broth and strain it into a bason, and scruze into it the juice of two or three lemmons. These were he ordinary morning draughts, with caudles, for variety, of the
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:56650:65"/>Protectress and her Master, and about 11 a clock, a cup of small Ale with a toast and sugar.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>How to make Barley-broth.</head>
               <p>TAke Barley and put in fair wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, give it three qualms over the fire, separate the waters, and put it into a cullender, boyl it in a fourth water, with a blade of mace and a clove, and when it is boyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away, put in some raisins and currants, and when the fruit is boyled enough, take it off and sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son it with white white, rose-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, butter and sugar, and a cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of yolks of egges beaten with it: This was a Mess frequently prepared for <hi>Oliver.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To make a Pudding of Hogs Liver another way.</head>
               <p>BOyl your Hogs Liver and grate it, put to it more grated bread then Liver, with as much fine
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:56650:66"/>flower, as of either, put twelve eggs to the value of a gallon of this mixture, with about two pound of beef suet minced small, with a pound and a half of cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, half a quarter of a pint of rose-water, a good quantity of cloves and mace, nutmeg, cinna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and ginger, all minced ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry small, mix all these with sweet milk and cream, let it be no thic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker then fritter batter: To fill your Hogs guts, you may make with it the maw fit to be eaten hot at Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; in your kniting or tying the guts, you must remember to give them three or four inches scope: In your putting them into the boyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing water, you must handle them round, to bring the meat equal to all parts of the gut, they will ask about half an hour boyling, the boyling must be sober, if the wind rise in them, you must be ready to prick them, or else they will flie and burst in pieces; This was Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>Frances</hi> her Delicacy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:56650:66"/>
               <head>How to make an Eels Pie, with Oysters.</head>
               <p>TAke the Eels, wash them and gut them, and dry them well in a cloath, to four good Eles al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low a pint of Oysters well washed, season them with pepper, salt, and nutmeg, and large mace, put half a pound of butter into the Pie, as also half a lemmon sliced, so bake it, when it is drawn, take the yolks of two Eggs, a couple of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chovies dissolved in a little white wine, with a quarter of a pound of fresh butter, melt it and mix altogether and make a Lear of it, and put into the Pie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>How to roast a Shoulder of Mutton with Oysters.</head>
               <p>YOur Oysters beign parboild, put to them some parsley, tyme, and winter savoury minced small, with the yolks of six eggs
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:56650:67"/>hard boiled and minced, a half-penny-loaf of grated bread, three or four yolks of eggs, so mingle all together with your hands, your Shoulder of Mutton being spitted, lay it upon the dresser and make holes with a sticking knife, in it (you may cut the holes as wide as you think convenient) put in your Oysters with the herbs and ingredients after them, about thirty Oysters will be enough; let it roast indifferent long, take the rest of a quart and put them into the deep dish, with claret wine, two or three onyons, in halves, a couple of minced ancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vies, put all this under your Mutton in the pan, so save your gravie, and when your meat is ready put your sauce upon a heap of coals, put to it the yolk of an egg beaten, a grated nutmeg and sweet butter, dish the Shoulder of Mutton, and pour this thick lear of Oysters all over it, and garnish it with barbaries and lemmons.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:56650:67"/>
               <head>How to piekle up Cucumbers.</head>
               <p>TAke young Gerkins, and wipe them clean, take the seeds of dill and fennel, large mace, beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en pepper and salt, season the beer vineger very well with salt, lay a layer of Cucumbers, and sprinkle between every row of Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbers, your seeds and season<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; When the pot is almost full with Cucumbers, fill it up to the brim with beer vineger, and keep it close covered; If you like broom buds rather, they are to be pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kled only with water and salt, and shut close as before; But I may add (to put the Cariors nose out of joynt) that onyons and water were the chief Court sauce, and shall hence forth be exalted and dignified by the name of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectors Hogo.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:56650:68"/>
               <head>How to make a fresh Cheese.</head>
               <p>I Have mentioned before her ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Butter, I shall now give you an Experiment of her making of fresh Cheese. Take some new milk or cream, and a race of cinnamon, scald it, then take it off the fire, sweeten it with fine suger, then take a spoonful of runnet to two quarts of milk, set it by and keep it close covered, and so let it stand, when the cheese comes, strow a little fine sugar, and grated nutmeg, and serve it in with sippits, sops in Sack or Muscadine; which at this season of the year, was one of the extem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore entertainments of this rusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Lady.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To roast a Lamb, or Kid.</head>
               <p>TRuss your Lamb or Kid, prick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the head backwards over the shoulder, laying it down, set
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:56650:68"/>it and lard it with Bacon, and draw it with time, and a little lemmon peel, then make a pud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding with a little grated bread, a handful of sweet herbs, a handful of beef suet, put in about a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of flower, and a little saffage with time, made mince meat, season it with cloves, mace, cinamon, ginger, nutmeg, and salt, make it up into a tender body, with two or three eggs, and a little bran, stuff it into the belly of the Lamb, and Kid, put some sauce of Veal or Lamb over it, so prick it up the belly, roast the Lamb and Kid, and when it is enough, serve it up with Venison sauce.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To roast Venison.</head>
               <p>THis is the same common way with roasting a Hogs harslet, and meerly devised, for to take off by its variety the nauseousness of this meat, which was in abundance at their Table, as shall further be
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:56650:69"/>manifested. Take the biggest part of the Hanch of Venison, and cut it in thin collops, hack it with your knife, as you do the like to Veal, then lard it very thick, with a small larding pin, then take a handful of parsley and spinnage, good store o<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tyme, a little Rosemary, winter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>savoury and sweet marjorum, mince it exceeding small, with a little beef-suet, so put it in the dish with your Venison; put to it some beaten cloves, cinnamon, nutmeg, with a pretty quantity of salt, the yolks of half a dozen of egges or more, mingle it up alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with your hands, then spit your colops on a small spit or long <hi>broaches</hi> made with sticks, you must spit them so by doubling of them or bringing in the ends, that they may not hang too long, but equal; when they are all spitted, put your herbs amongst them and tye them together with a pack-thread; as they roast put a dish under them with claret wine; when they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:56650:69"/>done, take your dish and set it on the coals, put grated bread, beaten cinnamon, vinegar and su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar to the wine, with a ladleful of drawn butter, dish up your Veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, and put on this lear, but very thin over it, and so serve it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>How to boyl a Hanch of Venison.</head>
               <p>THis was a truly Royal and constant dish in its season at Court, when it was so really, and therefore out of curiosity and state was served up to her Table during the season; it is more extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary then any of the former, but since her times destroyed the game, yet cheapned and aviled the Venison, and made it every ones meat; which sordid example yet prevails among some proprietors of parks: I will set down this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</p>
               <p>First, stuff your Venison with a handful of sweet herbs and parsley minced, with a little beef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suet, and yolks of egges boyled
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:56650:70"/>hard, season yourstuffing with pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, nutmeg, ginger and salt, put your Hanch of Venison a boyling, being powdered before, then boyl up three or four colly-flowers in strong broth, &amp; a little milk; when they are boyled, put them forth into a pipkin, add to them drawn butter, and keep them warm by the fire, then boyl up two or three handfuls of spinnage in the same liquor, when it is boyled up, pour out part of your broth, and put in a little vinegar, a ladleful of sweet butter, and a grated nutmeg, your dish being ready with sippets in the bottom, put on the spinnage round towards your dish side, then take up the Venison being boyled, and put it in the middle of your dish, and put in your colly-flowers all over it, pour on your sweet butter over your colly-flowers, and garnish it with barberries, and the brims of the dish with some green parsley minced; cabbage is as good done in the same manner as colly-flowers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:56650:70"/>
               <head>How to bak a Venison-Pasty.</head>
               <p>THis is called the King of dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which <hi>Oliver</hi> stole by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tail, (as he did a more real Regali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) many years before, and shared this soveraign delicacy among his Complices, but now more then bold <hi>Rebin Hood,</hi> he was Lord and avowed Master of the Game and therefore that his fellow Dear stealers may know how to dress their prey <hi>a la mode Cromwellian,</hi> take this Prescription, for to other persons it will be of no use: when you have powdered your Hanch of Venison, or the sides of it, by taking away all the bones and si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>news, and the skin or fat, season it with pepper and salt only, beat it with your rolling-pin, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion it for the Pasty, by taking away from one part and adding to another; your paste being made with a peck of fine flower, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout three pound of butter, and
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:56650:71"/>a dozen eggs, work it up with cold water into as stiff a paste as you can, drive it forth for your Pasty, let it be as thick as a mans thumb, roll It up upon a rolling-pin, and put under it a couple of sheets of cap-paper well flowered, then your white being already minced and beaten with water, proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it upon the Pasty, to the bredth and length of the Venison, so lay you Venison in the said white, wash it round with your feather, and put on a border; season your Venison at the top, and turn over your other leaf of paste, so close up your Pasty, then drive out ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther border for garnishing the sides up to the top of the Pasty, so close it up together by the rolling-pin, by rolling it up and down by the sides and ends; and when you have flourisht your garnishing, and edged your pasty, vent it at the top, set it into the Oven, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter four or five hours baking, at least, draw it. This will serve, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bating
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:56650:71"/>the time, for any other meats baking, for beef or mutton, and may be applied, which is the main design of this discovery, to vulgar use. I must omit Her man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of collering of Venison, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause not practicable among mean people.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To boyl any usual joint of Meat.</head>
               <p>CUt any of them in such large pieces as you usually do a neck of mutton, as that two or three of them may serve in a dish, and put them into a pot, with so much water as will cover them; if you have a line of mutton (the suet taken from it) or a neck of veal, you may take ten sprigs of winter-savoury, and as much of tyme, adding to them twelve great onyons, if they are small, take the more, grate to them half a penny loaf, with half an ounce of cloves and mace, and one hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of spinnage, a little salt and
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:56650:72"/>parsley (if in the Spring or Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, otherwise capers and sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiere) let it boyl moderately, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til it be half consumed; when you take it off, add a little vinegar and sweet burter, but you must not let your spinnage and parsley have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove a quarter of an hours boyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To bake Steaks the French way.</head>
               <p>SEason the Steaks with pepper, nutmeg and salt lightly, and set them by, then take a piece of the leanest of a leg of mutton and mince it small with some beef-suet, and a few sweet herbs, as tops of tyme and penny-royal, grated break, yolks of eggs, sweet cream, raisins of the sun, &amp;c. work all these together, and make it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to little balls or puddings, put them (into a deep round pye) on the Steaks, then put to them some butter, and sprinkle it with ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juice, close it up and bake it, when
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:56650:72"/>it is enough, cut it up and liquor it with the juice of two or three oranges or lemmons.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To bake a Pig.</head>
               <p>THis is an experiment practised by Her at <hi>Huntingdon</hi> Brew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>house, and is a singular and the only way of dressing a Pig. Take a good quantity of clay, such as they stop barrels bungs with, and having moulded it, stick your Pig, and blood him well, and when he is warm, arm him like a Curassier, or one of <hi>Cromwels</hi> Iron-sides, hair, skin, and all (his intrai's drawn and belly sowed up again) with this prepared clay, thick every where, then throw him below the stoak-hole under the Furnace, and there let him soak, turn him now and then, when the clay is hardned, for twelve hours, he is then sufficiently baked; then take him and break off the clay, which easily parts, and you will have a fine crispy coat,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:56650:73"/>and all the juice of the Pig in your dish; remember but to put a few leaves of sage, and a little salt in the belly of it, and you need no other sauce. The like you may do with any fowle whatsoever, for the clay will fetch off and consume the feathers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>Another way according to Court fashion.</head>
               <p>FLay a small fat Pig, cut it in quarters, or in smaller pieces, season it with pepper, ginger and salt, lay it into a fit coffin, strip and mince small a handful of parsley, six sprigs of winter-savoury, strew it on the meat in the Pye, and strew upon that the yolks of three or four hard eggs minced, and lay upon them five or six blades of mace, a handful of clusters of bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berries, a handful of currants well washed and picked, a little sugar, half a pound of sweet butter or more, close your Pye and set it in
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:56650:73"/>an Oven, as hot as for manchet, and in three hours it will be ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, draw it forth, and put in half a pint of sugar, being warmed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the fire, pour it all over the meat, and put on the pye lid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, scrape on sugar, and serve it hot on the Table.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To make a Fool.</head>
               <p>TAke two quarts of cream, set it over the fire and let it boyl, then take the yolks of twelve eggs and beat them very well with three or four spoonfuls of cold cream, and then strain the eggs in the skillet of the hot cream, stirring it all the time to keep it from burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, then set it on the fire, and let it boyl a little while, but keep it still stirring for fear of burning, so then take it off, and let it stand and cool, then take two or three spoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls of sack, and put it in the dish, with four or five sippets, set the dish and sippets a drying, and
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:56650:74"/>when they be dry that they hang to the dish, sweeten the cream and pour it into the dish softly, because the sippets shall not rise up; this will make three dishes, when it is cold it is fit to be eaten.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To make an Artichoak-Pye.</head>
               <p>TAke the bottom of six Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choaks, being boyled very tender, put them in a dish, and some vinegar over them, season them with ginger and sugar, a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle mace whole, and put them in a coffin of paste: when you lay them in, lay some marrow and dates sliced, &amp; a few raisins of the sun in the bottom, with good store of butter, when it is half baked, take a gill of sack, being boyled first with sugar, and a pill of orange, put it in the Pye, and set it in the Oven again till you use it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:56650:74"/>
               <head>To boyl Flounders or Jacks after the best manner.</head>
               <p>TAke a pint of white wine, the tops of young tyme and rose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary, and a little whole mace, a little whole pepper seasoned with verjuice, salt, and a piece of sweet butter, and so serve it; you may do fish in the same liquor three or four times.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To draw Butter, of only use in sauces.</head>
               <p>TAke the Butter and cut it into thin slices, put it into a dish, then put it upon the coals where it may melt leisurely, stir it often, and when it is melted, put in two or three spoonfuls of water or vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negar which you please, then stir it and beat it until it be thick, if the colour keep white it is good, but if it look yellow and curdly in boyling, it is nought, and not fit to be used to this purpose.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:56650:75"/>
               <head>To make puff-paste.</head>
               <p>BReak two egges in three pints of flower, make it with cold water, then rowl it out pretty thick and square, then take so much butter as paste, and divide your butter in five places, that you may lay it on at five several times, rowl your paste very broad, and take one part of the same butter in lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle pieces all over your paste, then throw a handful of flower slightly on, then fold up your paste, and beat it with a rolling-pin, so rowl it out again; thus do several times, and then make it up.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To make an excellent Jelly.</head>
               <p>TAke three gallons of fair wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, boyl in it a knuckle of veal, and two calves feet slit in two, with all the fat clean taken from between the clawes, so let them boyl to a very tender Jelly keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:56650:75"/>it clean scummed, and the ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the pot alwayes wiped with a clean cloth, that none of the scum may boyl in them, strain it from the meat, and let it stand all night, and the next morning take away the top and the bottom, and take to a quart of this Jelly half a pint of sherry sack, half an ounce of cinnamon, and as much sugar as will season it, six whites of eggs very well beaten; mingle all these together, then boyl it half an hour, and let it run through your Jelly bag.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>Another manner to make a fresh Cheese presently.</head>
               <p>TAke the whites of six eggs, beat them very well, and ring in the juice of a good lemmon to the whites, when the cream seetheth up, put in the whites and stir it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout till it be turned, and then take it off and put it into a cheese trough, and let the whay be drawn
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:56650:76"/>from it, then take the curd and pound it in a stone morter, with a little rose-water and sugar, and put it into an earthen cullender, and so let it stand till you send it to the Table, then put it into a dish, and put a little cream to it, and so serve it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To make a Cheese-cake the best way.</head>
               <p>TAke two gallons of new milk, put into it two spoonfuls and a half of runner, heat the milk little less then blood-warm, cover it close with a cloth, until you see the cheese be gathered, then with a secumming dish gently take out the whay, so when you have drain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the curd as clean as you can, put the curd into a sieve, and let it drain very well there, then to two quarts of curd take a quart of thick cream, a pound of sweet butter, twelve eggs, a pound and a half of currants, a penny worth of cloves, nutmeg and mace beaten,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:56650:76"/>half a pound of good sugar, a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of a pint of rose-water, so mingle it well together, and put it in puff-paste.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>Another way.</head>
               <p>PUt due quantity of runnet to three gallons of milk, that it it may be a tender curd, run it through a thin strainer, when it comes or gathereth, squeese or pres out the whay, as well as you can possible, put it into a deep bason, put to it about a pound of sweet butter melted, sixteen eggs, casting away half the whites, season it with beaten cinnamon, ginger, cloves, mace and nutmeg, some sugar sufficient to sweeten it, with some salt, eringo and citron minced, a handful of gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted bread or naples bisket, mix it all well together, if it be too stiff add a little sweet cream, let it not be too thin, so beat down the sides of your cakes; then make your
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:56650:77"/>cakes with melted butter, and warm your milk, with a handful of poudered sugar, rowl out your paste, and jag out your pattern by a large round trencher and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per thereon, then put on the sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soned curds by spoonfuls, and turn up the sides of it in six or eight corners, bake them in a quick O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, but not too hot. They will ask a quarter of an hours baking.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To broyl Oysters.</head>
               <p>TAke the biggest Oysters you can get, then take a little min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced tyme, grated nutmeg, and grated bread, and a little salt, put this to the Oysters, then get some of the largest bottom shells and place them on the gridiron, and put two or three Oysters in each shell, then put some butter to them, and let them simmer on the fire till the liquor bubbles low, supplying it still with butter, when they are crisp, feed them with
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:56650:77"/>white wine, and a little of their own liquor, with a little grated bread, nutmeg and minced tyme, but as much only as to relish it, so let it boyl up again, then add some drawn butter to thicken them, and dish them on a dish or plate, but if you have scollop shells it is the best way to broyl them in.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To broyl Scollops.</head>
               <p>FIrst boyl the Scollops, and then take them out of the shells and wash them, then slice them and season them with nutmeg, ginger and cinnamon, and put them into the bottom of your shells again, with a little butter, white wine and vinegar, and grated bread, let them be broyled on both sides; if they are sharp, they must have sugar added to them, for the fish is luscious and sweet naturally; there is therefore another proper way to broyl them, with Oyster li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:56650:78"/>and gravy, with dissolved an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chovies, minced onyons and tyme, with the juice of a lemmon in it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To stew a dish of Trouts.</head>
               <p>LEt your frying-pan be very hot with clarified butter, then split them in two, and give them a sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den brown with a forcible heat, and let a stewing dish be ready prepared with gravy, oyster li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor, a little claret wine and vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, fry three or four sliced ony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and when they are brown, put them to the fish, with a handful of parsley fryed green, a sliced nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meg, two or three anchovies, and let it just boyl up together, then dish up your Trouts upon sippets; notwithstanding the best way for crispness and sight of your fish, is to fry the split fish as Trout, Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Peel, and Salmon very crisp and brown; dish it up with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side uppermost.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:56650:78"/>
               <head>To stew a Carp.</head>
               <p>TAke a living Carp and knock him on the head, open him in the belly take heed you break not the gall, pour in a little vinegar, and wash out all the blood, stir it about with your hand, then keep it safe, then have a pan or skillet on the fire, with so much white wine as will almost cover the fish; put to it an onyon cut in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, a clove or less of garlick, a race of ginger shred, a nutmeg quarter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, a faggot or bundle of sweet herbs, three or four anchovies, your Carp being cut out and rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all over with salt, when the wine (if abated with a little water will do as well) doth boyl, put the Carp in, and cover him close, and let him stew up for about a quarter of an hour, then put in the blood and vinegar with a little butter, so dish up the Carp, and let the spawn, milt and revet be laid upon
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:56650:79"/>it, the liquor that boyled him, with the butter, is the best sauce, and is to be eaten as broth; garnish the dish with lemmons and grated broad.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To make a Warden or Pear Pye.</head>
               <p>BAke your Wardens or Pears in an Oven, with a little wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and good quantity of sugar, let your pot be covered with a piece of dough, let them not be fully baked by a quarter of an hour, when they are cold make a high coffin, and put them in whole, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to them some cloves, whole cinnamon, sugar with some of the liquor they were closed in, so bake it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To make a Quince Pye.</head>
               <p>CUt your Quinces from the core, and fill your Pye, lay o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it sliced oringado, and pour into it the syrrup of barberries,
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:56650:79"/>mulberries, oringado, and put on good store of sugar, with two or three sticks of cinnamon, so close and prick it, but give it as little vent as you can; you may also bake them whole, after you have cored them with your coring iron and and pared them very thin, when they are placed in your Pye, fill the vacant place where your core was taken out, with the syrrup of orangado, they ought to have as much sugar as their weight, but not if you have store of sweet syrrup.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To make a Pye with Pippins.</head>
               <p>YOu must core and pare your Pippins, and when your cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin is made, take a handful of sli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced quinces and strew over the bottom thereof, then place in your pippins, and fill the core holes with the syrrup of quinces, and put into every one a piece of orin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gado, so pour on the syrrup of
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:56650:80"/>quinces over the apples with sugar, and close it; these Pyes will ask good soaking, especially the quince Pye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To make a double Tart.</head>
               <p>TAke some codlings tenderly boyled and peel them, cut them in halves, fill your Tart, put into a quarter of a hundred of co<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>lings a pound and a half of su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, a few cloves, and a little cin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon, close up the coffin and bake it; when it comes out of the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, take a quart of cream, six eggs, a quartern of sugar and a sliced nutmeg, beat all these well toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, pour them into the Tart, then set your Tart in the Oven for half a quarter of an hour, when it comes out, cut off the ley and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a lid cut in flowers ready, lay it on, and garnish it with preserves of damsons, resberries, apricocks and cherries, and place a preserved quince in the middle, and strew it with sugar biskets.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:56650:80"/>
               <head>How to make an Almond Tart.</head>
               <p>RAise an excellent good past with six corners, an inch deep, take some blancht Almonds very finely beaten with rose-water, take a pound of sugar to a pound of Almonds, some grated nusmeg, a little cream, with strained spin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage as much as will colour the Almonds green, so bake it with a gentle heat in an Oven not shut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the lid, draw it, and stick it with candid Orange and Citron, and red and white Muskadine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To make white Quince Cakes.</head>
               <p>FIrst clarify the sugar with the white of an egg, but put not so much water to it as you do for Marmalade; before you clarify it, keep out almost a quarter of the su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, let your Quinces be scalded, and let them be chopped in small pieces before you put it into the
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:56650:81"/>syrrup, then make it boyl as fast as you can, and when you have scummed it, and you think it be half boyled, then jamire it, and let the other part of your sugar be ready candy'd to a hard candy, and so put them together, letting it boyl but a very little after the candy is put to it, then put in a little Musk, and so lay it out be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it be cold.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To make red Quince Cakes.</head>
               <p>BAke them in an Oven with some of their own juice, their own coars being cut or bruised and put to them, then weigh some of this juice with some of the Quince, being cut into small pieces taking their weight in sugar, and with the Quince, some pritty quantity of juice of Barberies, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing baked or stewed in a pot; when you have taken their weight in sugar, you must put the weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Quince, and above three quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:56650:81"/>of the sugar together, and put to it some little quantity of water as you shall see cause, but make not the syrrup too thinne; and when you have put all this to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, cover it, and set it to the fire, keep it covered, and skimme it as much as you can; when it is half boyled, then fimmer it; let the other part of sugar have no more water put to it, then well wet the sugar, and so let it be boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to a very hard candy, and when you think they be boyled enough, then lay them out before they be cold.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To make clear Cakes of Quince.</head>
               <p>YOu must prepare the Quinces and Barberies as before, and then take the clearest syrrup, and let it stand on the coals two or three hours, then take the weight of it in sugar, and put near half the su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar to the juice, and so let them boyl a little on the fire, and then
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:56650:82"/>candy the rest of the sugar very hard, and so put them together, stirring it while it is almost cold, and so put it into glasses.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="recipe">
               <head>To Preserve Quinces white.</head>
               <p>TAke to every pound of Quince, a pound an a quarter of sugar, clarify this sugar with the white of an egge, coar your Quinces but not too much, and then put this sugar, and water, and Quince, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing raw, together, and so make them boyl so fast as you can see no Quince, but forget not to turn them, and take off what skimme you can, keep them boyling thus fast, till you think they be ENOUGH.</p>
               <p>AND so I have run through the whole and more usual fare of her private Table, observing no me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod therein, because I had them in this form from a near servant of hers? As for Fish and Flesh days,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:56650:82"/>there was no observation of them, all dayes being alike to the Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer and Purveyour, and those that eat at her Tables, as was hinted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
               <p>But this habit of Diet, not prov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing effectual to the prolongation of <hi>Olivers</hi> life, by and with which this Court subsisted, and was the onely ligament of that riffraff So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety; a Voyder was the next ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; for though there were some faint and slight shewes of House-keeping, which the standing Court Officers maintained with their cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit (and injury of several persons, who trusted upon the greatness of the deceased Usurper) to keep their places warm, and themselves in action; yet Mrs. <hi>Cromwel,</hi> wisely and timely withdrew her stake, and suffered her Son <hi>Ricardo,</hi> to run the resque of the old and new debt upon his own Score.</p>
               <p>And upon his account, meerly was that costly solemnity of <hi>Olivers</hi> Funerals advised, on purpose to
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:56650:83"/>bankrupt him: the pomp bestow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the dead, proving the ruine and disgrace of the living; so that all things went backward with him with double the pace they flowed upon his Father, and in the same manner; for whereas his Father was wont to call in the Guards, to eat the reliques of his Victuals, now they rushed in, and perforce took the meat off his Table, with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of their Pay and Arrears, and this with so much insolence, that Mrs. <hi>Cromwel,</hi> the afflicted Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of this Unfortunatus, could not forbear in anger to tell her Son <hi>Fleetwood,</hi> That <hi>he had brought his hoggs to a fair Market:</hi> nor is all that Droll, which is mentioned of her in a Play, called <hi>The Rump, or Mirrour of the Times.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now is it time to take leave of this good Huswife ere while so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journing with her Son <hi>Henry,</hi> and her Daughter <hi>Francis,</hi> inter marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Sir <hi>William Russels</hi> Son, so that there is a cross match betwixt the
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:56650:83"/>Families; <hi>Henry</hi> having married his Daughter before, but she is now at <hi>Hurley</hi> in <hi>Hampshire,</hi> with her Daughter in Law <hi>Richard Cromwels</hi> wife, while he absents himself for his Debts, which the kind Rump undertook for to pay in consideration, and as the value of his resigning the Government: And this is the latest Intelligence of those illustrious Bubbles and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geants of fortune, which once fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the world with admiration and discourse, but are now become the contempt and by-word of the meanest of the people, who mingle their curses with their scorn, and assist their lingring envious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stiny, with all the dicteries and reproaches, which the arrogance and guilt of their Usurpation, can suggest to the passions of enraged minds. And this Essay and <hi>quel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que chose</hi> is added to help their <hi>Digestion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sic erit Aeternum Pontiliana,</hi> Vale.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>